<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The heroicall deuises of M. Claudius Paradin Canon of Beauieu. Whereunto are added the Lord Gabriel Symeons and others. Translated out of Latin into English by P.S.</title>
            <title>Devises héroiques. English</title>
            <author>Paradin, Claude, 16th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 210 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19183</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119509</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854716</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854716</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20154</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08907)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20154)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 968:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The heroicall deuises of M. Claudius Paradin Canon of Beauieu. Whereunto are added the Lord Gabriel Symeons and others. Translated out of Latin into English by P.S.</title>
                  <title>Devises héroiques. English</title>
                  <author>Paradin, Claude, 16th cent.</author>
                  <author>P. S., fl. 1591.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 374 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by William Kearney dwelling in Adlingstreete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Heroical deuises.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Emblems --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20154:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20154:1"/>
            <p>THE HEROICALL DEVISES OF M. CLAVDIVS PARADIN Canon of Beauicu.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto are added the Lord Gabriel Symeons and others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Latin into Engliſh by P. S.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of William Kearney</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Imprinted by William Kearney dwelling in Adlingſtreete. 1591.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20154:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20154:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL THE RENOWMED CAPTEINE Chriſtopher Carleill Eſquier, chiefe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of her Maieſties forces in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince of Vlder in the Realme of Ireland, and Seneſhall there of the Countries of Clande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy, the Rowte, the Glins, the Duffre, and Kylultaugh.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Worſhipfull, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mindfull of the ſaying which the auncient poet <hi>Heſiod</hi> vſeth, whereby he doth iuſtly admoniſh (as imitating the earth) to recompence benefites with increaſe, though I diſpaire to requite your manie curteſies affoorded me, &amp; ſo muſt be checked of that dumbe
<pb facs="tcp:20154:3"/>creature, yet I intende to imitate the the rockes and anſwer ſo loud a voice with a reſounding Echo, and though in compariſon of the voice I ſpeake but the laſt ſillable, yet I hope your Worſhip regarding rather my good meaning than my gift, will affoord your patronage to this little booke, &amp; ſhrowd it vnder the protection of your Heroicall ſpirit, where I doubt not it ſhall obtaine fauour, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by find paſſage without repulſe: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo it containeth in it that which moſt men deſire, both delight to the eye and harmonie to the eare, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to both and offence to none. I haue the rather preſumed to hope of your Worſhips good acceptance for two cauſes: the one for that I ſee the like to haue ben done in the ſame booke being in French and Latin by verie honorable and vertuous perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, to whom in mine account your
<pb facs="tcp:20154:3"/>Worſhip is nothing inferior. For to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit al diſcourſe and to touch only the bare names of ſome things managed by your ſelfe: Let the ſundrie great proofes of your martiall ſeruices and worthie aduentures as well by land as by ſea witnes what your deſerts haue bene, which the Spaniſh weſt India with loſſe and griefe; Muſcouia or Ruſſia with worthy commendation; France, the Low Countries, and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, with renowmed fame haue with generall voice and conſenting occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie, euen from them all to both farre and neere ſounded &amp; emblaſed, wherein can not be forgotten your zeale alwaies ſhewed towards Chriſts Goſpell, beſides manie other your rare vertues acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with a chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full liberalitie and a moſt curteous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fabilitie towards all men, whereof my ſelfe among the reſt haue ſufficiently taſted from time to time. The other
<pb facs="tcp:20154:4"/>for that ſometimes I haue noted your Worſhip to be well delighted with the ſubſtance &amp; nature of this worke, as well in your beholding of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens Emblemes, which haue bin worthie perſonages, as alſo in your deuiſing &amp; ſetting downe ſome from your owne conceit, which if I coulde haue recouered, as once I was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſhewed ſome of them by one of your ſeruantes, who is now in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, I had here adioined them vnto the others. And ſo fearing I haue ben ſomewhat too tedious I humbly take my leaue in recommending my labor to your good fauour, and my ſelfe to do you ſeruice in any thing I may be able. London the third of Ianuarie. 1591.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips moſt humble to command <hi>William Kearney.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20154:4"/>
            <head>To the moſt worthie knight Theodot of Marze, Lord of Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roche, Laſſenaz, &amp;c. Claudius Paradin ſendeth greeting.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S varietie of pictures yeeldeth great pleaſure and recreation vnto man: ſo likevviſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and commoditie that is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from them, is not to be had in little regard or eſtimation, foraſmuch as by the vſe of them vexations both of bodie and minde (vvhich are othervviſe intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) are eaſily mollified and aſſvvaged. The truth hereof hath beene at all times vvell knovvne to our auncestors, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them especially to great kings, princes and potentates, vvhich carrying at all ſeaſons in their hautie and heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call minds, an expreſſe patterne &amp; image of vertue, haue hereby continued a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall memorie of the ſame, being verie apt in his ovvne nature to decay and be forgotten. The first and originall cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:20154:5"/>of this practiſe vvas this, that diuerſe men according to the diuerſitie of their ſpeciall conceites and inuentions, vvere giuen to repreſent and expreſſe the ſame vvith ſundrie formes and pictures, as it ſtood most vvith ech mans fanſie &amp; good liking. Theſe their deuiſes being thus ſet dovvne in picture, are tearmed their armes, for that they vvere painted in their armes and in their bucklers, targets or other militarie furnitures: for they tooke great pleaſure to commende and beautifie in any ſort, that thing in the vvhich they repoſed a great hope of their ſecuritie: and in their vvarres vvhere death vvas alvvaies preſent before their eyes, they deſired continually to carrie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them theſe deuiſes, vovving as it vvere therby as vvel to die as liue vvith theſe monuments and memorials of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. This commendable practiſe grovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by little &amp; little, vvas at length aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented vvith the addition of certaine ſhort and pithie ſentences for the better
<pb facs="tcp:20154:5"/>information of ſuch as vvere learned, vvhich being ioyned vvith the former deuiſes are vſed by certaine noble perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages vntill this preſent age, as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth manifeſtly in the ſumptuous buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and ſtately Courtes of great kings and princes, vvhich are ſo copiouſly enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vvith ſuch Emblemes and monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that this practiſe ſeemeth to be more esteemed in theſe our daies than in anie former ages. Wherefore vvhen I conſidered all theſe things vvith my ſelfe and vvithall at the vnestimable benefit &amp; commoditie of theſe pictures, I thoght it not altogither vnprofitable to bestowe ſometime in coupling and gathering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of ſuch amongst the rest, as either were chiefely commended vnto vs by our anceſtors, or are ſpecially vſed amongest great men at this day, or elſe are founde in the olde histories to be most memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable &amp; of principal note &amp; regard. And in ſo doing as the olde Aegiptians vvere
<pb facs="tcp:20154:6"/>wont to expreſſe their intentes and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings by their Hierographicall letters: ſo hope I by this meanes to ſtirre vp diuerſe men to the apprehenſion and loue of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and for that cauſe I haue hereunto the rather added<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> certaine ſcholies or briefe notes for the better vnderſtanding of ſuch matters, vvhich othervviſe ſeme to containe ſome difficultie. And vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as (right Noble Sir) you are alvvaies gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, according to the naturall diſpoſition of your anceſtors, to al good knowledge &amp; vertuous exerciſe, I am emboldned to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vnto you this ſmall packet of Deuiſes, as a pledge of the good vvill and affection that I haue to do you ſeruice, aſſuring my ſelfe that you vvill take no leſſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in peruſing of them, than you haue alvvaies, had delight to ſee vertue in any ſort reuerenced or exalted.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20154:6"/>
            <head>DEVISES.</head>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Nullis praeſentior aether. God is more fauourable to none.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:20154:7"/>The letter TAV ſaith Hierome (vpon Marke) being one of the Hebrew Alphaber,<note place="margin">Hierome in Eze. 9.</note> is a moſt healthfull and ſacred letter, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a true note or type of the croſſe it ſelfe, &amp; becauſe that this letter in the holie tongue ſignifieth a marke. Some partly, who mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ouer the abhomination of Ieruſalem to bee marked, whereby they were ſaued in the midſt of the wicked, who by the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God were all ſodenly deſtroyed. Moreouer Tau ſignifieth a fal perfection, and therefore it is the laſt letter of the Hebrew Alphabet, as both ending and perfecting the ſame. Whereof alſo they make a great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, eſpecially whereas our redeemer Chriſt being nayled to the croſſe, before hee gaue vp the Ghoſt, burſt forth into theſe words: <hi>Conſummatumest,</hi> it is ended, or finiſhed: thereby declaring the type of all Propheſies, and holie ſcriptures, that is, euen the verie ſame houre that he was faſtned to the tree, ſhewing that the accompliſhment of this let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was performed. Which letter, although it ſurely tend vnto a figure; yet deſcribed by the manifeſt character, it farre plainer ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the figure of the croſſe, than otherwiſe. And therefore both the Greekes and Latines to this day do write it in forme of a croſſe.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20154:7"/>This letter therefore is a moſt proper and true badge or cognizance of all thoſe that being muſtered do warre in the Church of Chriſt to the worldes end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20154:8"/>
               <head>Manet inſontem grauis exitus. Great calamitie or affliction abideth the godly in this life.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:20154:8"/>Orus Apollo writeth,<note place="margin">Or. Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that the Aegyptians counted the figure of two lines one againſt the other, that is, of one perpendicular vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a diametrall, in ſignification of the life to come, amongſt the hieroglyphicall notes, or characters, neither could they render any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon hereof, then that it ſeemed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be a certaine ſigne of ſome diuine mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie. And therefore they imprinted it vpon the breſt of Serapis their Idoll, in that temple which vnder Theodoſius the Emperour was vtterly ouerthrowne, and laide louell with the ground. In which Temple were to be ſeene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where the hieroglyphicall letters, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the forme of a croſſe,<note place="margin">Suidas. Iſidorus</note> as Suidas wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Iſidorus affirmerh they vſed to note thoſe in their Ephemerides orregiſters, which either had eſcaped out of battell aliue, or which had died there with this letter θ. no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſlaine as it were with a dart thruſt thorow them, the liuing with this marke or letter T. Moreouer Aſc. Pedian ſaith,<note place="margin">Aſc. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian.</note> that the lottes which were vſed in iudgementes, were marked with three Characters: thoſe that were condemned to death with θ. thoſe that were abſolued with T. and thoſe that were more exactly to be examined with Δ.<note place="margin">Orus</note> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally euen in the Church of God ſome haue
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20154:9"/>too ſuperſtitiouſly dreamed this letter to be a ſacred and healthfull ſigne, and this phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall dreame hath growne vp and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued theſe many ages. And therefore ſome haue imagined Moyſes, whileſt he praied to the Lord in the Mountaine,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xod. 17.</note> his bodie vpon the ground proſtrated and his armes ſpread abroad in forme of a croſſe, and lifting vp his handes in a miſticall type, the Iſraelites ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came: when he fainted, the Iſraelites were put to the worſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:20154:9"/>
               <head>Secum feret omnia mortis. He carieth with him the ſignes of death.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:20154:10"/>The braſen Serpent erected by Moſes the conductor of the Iſraelites in the wildernes, (which being looked vpon, healed thoſe that were ſtoong with firy Serpents,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 21.</note> and deſtined to death) did prefigurate and foreſhew our ſaluation and redemption in Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:20154:10"/>
               <head>Hic ratio tentandi aditus. This is the way to enter into glorie.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20154:11"/>The Key whereof the Prophet Eſaias ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention,<note place="margin">Eſai. 22.</note> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe wordes. And I will giue vnto him the Key of the houſe of Dauid, he ſhall open and no man ſhall ſhu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and he ſhall ſhut, and no man ſhall open, did ſignifie in like maner the power and authoritie of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt in his Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:20154:11"/>
               <head>Pignora cara ſui. The pledges of her remembrance.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:20154:12"/>Concerning the Croſſe of our Sauiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt the redeemer of the worlde, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> myſterie of his bodie and blood, the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ieremy vnder the perſon of the wicked nation of the Iewes foreſpoke,<note place="margin">Ier. 11.</note> ſaying, <hi>Mittamus lignum in panem eius.</hi> Let vs make woo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his meate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:20154:12"/>
               <head>Animis illabere noſtris. How the wicked ſpirit entereth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our mindes.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The wicked ſpirit at his firſt beginning is pleaſant and plauſible, but at the laſt, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth man aſtoniſhed and altogither forgetful of himſelfe. Contrariwiſe, the holie ſpirit, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit at his verie firſt entrance he ſomewhat terrifieth and ſhaketh the mind, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he maketh it calme, quiet, &amp; ſecure, repleniſhing it with true and inward pleaſure. Which thing to haue hapned to the apoſtles
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20154:13"/>vpon the day of Penticoſt, the Actes do wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, the holie Ghoſt comming downe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> likenes of firy tongues, and lightning vpp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20154:13"/>
               <head>Fortuna mutata fidem nouanit. When Fortune frowneth, faith is chaunged.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>When Childericus fourth King of France for his infamous life, ſhould giue ouer his Kingdome, G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imcus a man entirely beloued of him, aduertiſed him to goe into Thuring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20154:14"/>whileſt he ſtaide to perfect the peace, &amp; brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a peece of gold in the midſt, gaue vnto him the one part thereof, to the intent tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame being ſent againe as he had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, when oportunitie ſerued, and being ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the other with equall coniuncture might confirme the certeintie of the thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> done to Childericus, &amp; of his returne. Whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing came to paſſe, for no ſooner had Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus deſiſted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his enterpriſe of peacema king, than Gillion a citizen of Rome wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thruſt from the poſſeſſion of the kingdome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> France, which he affirmed apperteined <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him, Childericus being reſtored to his form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſtate againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:20154:14"/>
               <head>Nutriſco, &amp; extinguo. I nouriſh, and I extinguiſh.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The Salamander lying in the fire, was the badge or Cognizance of Frances king of France. Which worme, Plinie writeth,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> is of ſuch a cold nature that ſhe quencheth the fire like iſe. Others write that ſhe liueth, &amp; is nori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20154:15"/>in the fire. I remember that I my ſelfe haue ſeene the picture of this King in a ſmall forme, ingrauen in braſſe: vpon whoſe backe part was placed an effigie of a firie Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with this inſcription, <hi>Nutriſco il buono, &amp; ſpengo il reo,</hi> that is, I nouriſh the vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and deſtroy the wicked. The ſame haue I ſeeme alſo in diuers places vpon walles, and namely a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Fontem Bellaqueum,</hi> moſt liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poliſhed and adorned in cloth of Tapeſtrie, Arraſe, and the like, with theſe verſes.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The cruell Beare, the Eagle ſwift,</l>
                  <l>and Snake that bites by day:</l>
                  <l>O Salamander to thy flame,</l>
                  <l>giue place without delay.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:20154:15"/>
               <head>Monſtrant Regibus aſtra viam. The heuens declare to men the way to follow.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The order of ſtarred Knights was publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtituted by King Iohn, in the Church at Saint Ouen in France, about the yeare of our Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d God 1351. which Knightes we are this ſigne of the Starre on their gownes, hats,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20154:16"/>or other place where it might eaſily be ſeene in Theaters, and Stages. And truly it is to be thought that this honorable cognizance had his beginning of the commemoration of that wonderfull ſtarre, which conducted the wiſe men from the Eaſt, to the place where Chriſt was borne. Whither alſo thoſe verſes may be referred, otherwiſe dedicate by Virgill the ſonne of Pollio, to Iulius Caeſar, concerning the commet which appeared after his death.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Behold the ſtarre of Dioneus Caeſar,</l>
                  <l>the ſtar wherin the corns reioice their fils,</l>
                  <l>And whereby eke the Grapes do take</l>
                  <l>their die on ſhadie hils.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:20154:16"/>
               <head>Donec totum impleat orbem. Till he repleniſh the whole world.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The increaſe of the moone in the daies of the moſt famous king Henry the ſecond king of France, was moſt ſtrange and prodigious. In the holy ſcriptures, the moone many times
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20154:17"/>doth ſignifie the Church: wherto may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the conſent of Paulus Aemilius in the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonie of Pope Calixtus the ſecond (whoſe name before was Guido, the ſonne of William Earle of the Heduans, or Burgundians.) who the day before his pontificall creation ſaw in a viſion a Starre carried by a childe from the ſide of the Moone. Furthermore the Moone is alwaies ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect to alteration, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> both increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth and decreaſeth at certcine houres and times. In like maner may wee ſee the Church of God militant, and neuer continuing in one and the ſame ſtate, but one while mainteined and defended of Chriſtian Princes, an other-while tyrannized, put to flight, and ſent in fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with factions of heretiques: whereby it commeth to paſſe, that it is neuer free from vexation and trouble in this life. Wherto not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Maieſtie of God the King himſelfe, and his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed certeine helpe and defence, vntill it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gathered vnder one God, one King, and one law, the moſt louing vnitie, &amp; immenſitie of the whole flocke, acknowledging one onely paſtor, may appeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:20154:17"/>
               <head>Immensi tremor Oceani. The trembling feare of the Ocean Sea.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Lodouicus the eleuenth King of France, when he was about to inſtitute the order of Saint Michaell (as they call it) in the yeare of our Lord 1469. for a Cognizance or Simbole he enſigned them with a golden chaine line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20154:18"/>togither with cockle-ſtones, and double knots, with circles of gold: in the midſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was a knob or muſhrome, as it were a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montorie with the golden image of Saint Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael hanging downe vppon their breſtes. Which laſt he did, being prouoked thereto by the example of king Charles the ſeuenth his father, who vſed the ſame image for his enſign in wars, taking the beginning of his mangu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration at Rothomage. Which cuſtome was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, &amp; afterwardes confirmed amongſt many kings, through a notable miracle or viſion (as they ſuperſtitiouſly dreame) of S. Michael ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the battell by the bridge of the citie of Orleance, who expulſed &amp; droue away the Engliſh men, and ſet the Citie free from their ſiege. The chaine therefore is a type or figure of this order, a ſigne of vertue, concord, and of a perpetuall league or couenant of amitie and friendſhip to be continued amongſt them, alſo a cognizance or badge of thoſe that deſerued well, and of the victorie obteined. By the gold he would haue to be vnderſtood, magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, proweſſe and honours. By the cockles, their mutuall equalitie or common condition of fortune: imitating herein the order of the Romane Senators, who vſed to weare cockles vpon their ſleeues: by the tying of them togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20154:18"/>with a double knot, he would repreſent the indiſſoluble couenant made betwixt him and the reſt, and that with no friuolous ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Laſt of all, by the image, he would ſhuld be declared the victorie and triumph which Michaell had ouer the diuell, whom he ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came. The reaſon of which ſigne doth greatly appertaine as well to the regiment and maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of a kingdome, as alſo to ſtrike feare and terrour into the enemy. And how many he thought good to be admitted into the ſocietie of this order, he himſelfe declared, to wit, 36. as it were patrones of the kingdome, amongſt whome he would be counted the firſt or chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. And therefore the ſame time, that he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined this order to be celebrate, he named fifteene lordes, whom for honours ſake, and prerogatiue of their names, it is not conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to omit with ſilence. The firſt therefore were theſe:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Charles Duke of Guienne.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Duke of Burbon and Auergne.</item>
                  <item>Lewis of Luxenburg Earle of Saint Paul, and Conſtable of France.</item>
                  <item>Andrew Lauallius, lord of Loheac, Marſhall of France.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Earle Sanſerre lord of Bueile.</item>
                  <item>Lewis Beaumont, lord of Foreſt and Pleſſis.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:20154:19"/>Lewis Deſtouteuille, lord of Torcy.</item>
                  <item>Lewis Lauall, lord of Chaſtillon.</item>
                  <item>Lewis baſtard of Burbon, Earle, Roſillon Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall of France.</item>
                  <item>Anthonie Chaban, Earle of Dammartin, chief Steward to the King.</item>
                  <item>Iohn baſtard of Armignia, Earle of Comin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, Marſhall of France, gouernour of Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phine.</item>
                  <item>George Trimoille, lord of Craon.</item>
                  <item>Gilbert Chaban, lord of Curton, Seneſhall of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cone.</item>
                  <item>Charles lord of Cruſſol, Seneſchal of Poicton.</item>
                  <item>Taneguius of Caſtell, gouernor of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces of Roſſillon, and Sardinia.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:20154:19"/>
               <head>Vltus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> He hath reuenged his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> quarrell, by the example of T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o).</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Lewis the 12. King of France, as Duke of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leance by diſcent, and earle of Blofie, gaue the Porcupine in his enſigne, with which ſimbole togither with the image of a Wolfe, the auncient Citie of Blofie was wont to blaze
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20154:20"/>their enſignes. This is to be ſeene grauen in many ſtones and walls.<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> Which beaſt nature hath ſo ſtudiouſly furniſhed with weapons, that ſhe may reſiſt al thoſe that withſtand her, eſpecially dogges, againſt whom ſhe throweth her prickes like violent arrowes. The interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of which portraiture, the ſtately houſes of a certaine noble citizen in that citie doe declare, at the entrance whereof, vnder the Porcupine theſe verſes are found ingrauen in ſtone.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Theſe Dartes are peace to humble men,</l>
                  <l>but warre to proud indeed:</l>
                  <l>For why? both life and death alſo,</l>
                  <l>from our woundes do proceed.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:20154:20"/>
               <head>Non ſine cauſa. Not without cauſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:20154:21"/>The iuſt and vpright ad miniſtration of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, with the due puniſhment of the wicked, is a thing ſo neceſſarie to kingdomes, peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and Countries, that if they ſhould bee taken away, the companies and ſocieties of men would ſoone fall to decaie and bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. Wherefore Rulers and Magiſtrates may righthe chalenge the ſworde to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, with publike and priuate honours, as warranted by the word of God, that they may bee not onclie a helpe and a comfort to the godlie and meeke, but alſo a feare and terrour to the wicked. Therefore is the moſte wholeſome dectrine of the Apoſtle Saint Paule to bee imbraced.<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> Wilt not thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (ſaith hee) feare the powers. Doe well then, and thou ſhalt haue praiſe thereby, for hee is the miniſter of God for thy good. But i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou doeſt euill, feare, for hee carrieth not the ſworde for naught, for hee is the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of God to reuenge in wrath to him that doth euill. Therefore bee ye ſubiect of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, not onelie for feare of anger, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for conſcience ſake. For this cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe ye pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e tribu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, they are the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uing for that purpoſe. Giue therefore to all men that which is due, tribute to whom tribute belongeth, feare to whom
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20154:21"/>feare apperteineth, and honour to whom ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour belongeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:20154:22"/>
               <head>Plus oultre. Hee conceiueth hope to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed further.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:20154:22"/>Charles the fift of immortall fame, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Rome, expreſſing euer in all his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and exploites, a certeine maieſtie and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, manifeſted his magnanimitie and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liancie in two pillers, which our anceſtors cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Hercules pillers, which are two promonto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries or hilles diſtant one from an other 700. paces, the one being in Mauritania towardes Affrike, called Abila, the other in the coaſt of the kingdome of Granalia towardes Spaine, called Calpe, betwixt the which runneth a gulph of the ſea, which men call Gibraltar, or the ſtraight of Seuille or Hiſpalenſe. Poets faine, that in this ſtraight ſometime ſtood a great rocke of a maruellous hugenes, ſtopping the courſe of the ſea for running that way, which being taken away by the ſtrength and induſtry of Hercules, there was paſſage made to the Ocean ſea. And for the remembrance of ſo worthie a benefite, they ſay two pillers were erected of him there, in the two chiefeſt partes of the world, Affricke and Europe. And truely as they in olde time had a great care to keepe from obliuion their noble geſtes, &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant deedes, recording them in their monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, regiſters, and the like (as they write, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander did his marſhall exploites) ſo Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les making an end there of his iournies and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20154:23"/>trauels, erected (as may be ſuppoſed) two me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable pillers, which whither they were made by nature, by art, or by force, it is not thorowly knowne. But this is certaine that there ſtood a church there, where in it is ſaid. Hanniball offred ſacrifice when he warred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Italy, where it is manifeſt, were two pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of braſſe, either of them eight cubits high, of an exellent fairenes. This place is called of the common ſort the doore-threſhald of the world, beyond which they ſay, neither anie man ſailed, till the time of Charles the fifth, which being ſearched out by his nauy, togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the nauy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Portugals, they found the fortunate iles, and ſundrie rich nations both towardes the Eaſt, and Weſt partes, for which cauſe, and to the end he might ſignifie to all poſterities the exellency and greatnes of his actes, he vſed this pozie or Apothegme <hi>Plus Oultre,</hi> that is further or beyond, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing great hope to goe forward further.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:20154:23"/>
               <head>Imperium ſine fine dedi. I haue giuen him rule without end or meaſure.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Auguſtus Ceaſar a moſt quiet and peaceable Emperor, hauing got into his hands the whole monarchie of the world, and being borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20154:24"/>the ſigne of Capricorne, held the ſame in ſuch eſtimation, that he cauſed the ſame ſigne of Capricornus to be imprinted vppon his coyne: hereby referring the luckie and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne preſagie of his fortune to the ſaid ſtarre or planet. Yea there are extant to this day both gold and ſiluer coyne, with this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Capticornus vpon them, the feete whereof conteine the ſphere of the world, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing alſo vpon the backſide a band of ſoldiers or the effigie of Amalthea, which laſt is found vpon the gold: vpon the ſiluer is the ſterne or forepart of a ſhip, in forme of an orbe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> circle. Both of them hauing this inſcription Auguſtus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:20154:24"/>
               <head>Inextricabilis error. Error is inextricable.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Auguſtus Caeſar, in the beginning of his raigne vſed the Monkey or Marmſet, as a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular ſecrete ſigne, ſignifying thereby, that the ſerious matters of a Prince, with his waightie affaires are not to be committed to the common people. Of which ſort eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are all holy and diuine things, leſt thorow the want of authoritie, they become baſe and contemptible. The ſame reaſon in a manner moued the Egyptians to picture in their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20154:25"/>the Marmſet or Monkey.<note place="margin">Celius.</note> Auguſtus Caeſar (as Plinie witneſſeth) hauing found two ſuch Monkeyes or Marmſets amongſt his mothers rings made by ſuch wonderful art,<note place="margin">Plinius.</note> and ſo like, that the one could by no means be diſcerned from the other: with the one wherof, as with a ſeale his actes and edicts in time of war were ſealed, reſpect being had as wel of the time as of the cauſes.<note place="margin">Dion.</note> Dion reporteth that Auguſtus Caeſar being occupied in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wars of Atty, gaue liſence to Agrippa, &amp; Mecenas chiefe rulers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romaine affaires to ſeale writings before they were preſented to the Senate: &amp; therefore they receiued a ſeale of Auguſtus, bearing the image of the Monkey or Marmſet. Which thing notwithſtanding was not done without deriſion,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> as Plinie recordeth, for the enigmes which the Monkey pretended, a prouerbe or by-word riſing thereof,<note place="margin">Sueton.</note> to wit, it is no maruell if the Monkey vtter hard and obſcure things. Therefore Auguſtus to avoid theſe ieſts and flouts, abſtained altogither from his ſuſpected &amp; vniuſt maner of ſealing, changing his ſeale into the image of Alexander the great. At the laſt, he imprinted it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his own natural picture or image, which afterward Tiberius, Caligula, Claudius Caeſar, Domicianus, &amp; other Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors ſucceeding in the ſame order, did vſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:20154:25"/>
               <head>Securitas altera. A ſecond ſecuritie or ſafetie.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:20154:26"/>Henrie the eight King of England, vſed a percullice of yron for a ſimbole, or ſigne, which is an engine of defence, vſed for the moſt part in gates and portes of cities and townes. Such an other kind of militarie ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem was there deuiſed at Rome (as Appian writeth) in the time of ciuill diſcention,<note place="margin">Appian.</note> when Scilla chalenging the empire to himſelf, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw the armie of Carbonians, preſſing to enter in by the gate of Collina: for letting fal the percullice, many of the Senators, and thoſe that were of the Carbonian faction were all ſlaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:20154:26"/>
               <head>Dederitne viam caſùſue, Deuſue. Whether Fortune or God doth giue the way.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cronicles of Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine.</note>Cronicles do record the noblenes and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the houſe of Lorraine: to wit, three birdes thruſt thorow with an arrow,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20154:27"/>which Godfray of Bullaine ſhot againſt Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids towre, being ſhewed in militarie ſigne by the beſieging of Ieruſalem. Which was ſigne of his highnes, authoritie, and princely dignitie, with the building of Ieruſalem. The dukes of Lorraine being enſigned with this embleme of the birds thruſt thorow, do teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſame, for in their coyne to this day they keepe it verie religiouſlie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:20154:27"/>
               <head>Fortitudo eius Rhodum tenuit. His valiancie wan and poſſeſſed the Rhodes.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Amatus Vertius y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fift knight of Subaudia, gaue a moſt royall &amp; magnificall name to an order of knights firſt inuented by him. Theſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20154:28"/>Knights he would haue to be innobled with golden chaine, wrought with moſt ſubtile, called loue knots, knit togither with great cunning, &amp; foure letters interlaced of equall diſtance one from another, hanging at the end therof the image &amp; hiſtorie of the angels meſſage to the virgine Marie. The letters and the pozie do ſignifie the greatnes of the glory that Amatus the firſt Knight and his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors had. For whileſt he went to Rhodes with his nauie to fight againſt the enimies of Chriſt, he well deſerued of Rhodia both of Knighthood, and Religion. And being made gouernor of that order, and of the garriſons alſo, he vndertooke the adminiſtration of the Rhodian warres, and bequeathed the ſame to his next ſucceſſor, he deliuered the caſtle of Acrenſe from ſiege, and remouing all feare both of danger and tyranny, he brought great ioy, and libertie to the Rhodians. Therefore he cauſed himſelfe to be named the firſt, in the catelogue of Knights, conſtituting foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene moe: all which he dignified with the ſame chaine of gold. The names of them that he knighted were theſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The ſaid Earle Vert.</l>
                  <l>Amé Earle of Geneua.</l>
                  <l>Antonie Lord of Belauieu.</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:20154:28"/>
                  <l>Hugh Challon Lord of Arlay.</l>
                  <l>Amé of Geneua.</l>
                  <l>Iohn of Vienne admiral of France.</l>
                  <l>William of Grandzon.</l>
                  <l>William of Chalamon.</l>
                  <l>Rowland Veyſſy of Burbon.</l>
                  <l>Stephen the baſtard ſon of Baume.</l>
                  <l>Iaſper of Monmeur.</l>
                  <l>Barlus of Foras.</l>
                  <l>Thennard of Menthon.</l>
                  <l>Amé Bonnard.</l>
                  <l>Richard Muſard an Engliſhman.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:20154:29"/>
               <head>Non inferiora ſecutus. Following no meane things.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:20154:29"/>Margaret Queene of Nauarre vſed a moſt ſolemne ſigne, namely the marigold, whoſe colour reſembleth ſo neere the colour of the ſonne, as almoſt nothing more. For what way ſo euer the ſunne goeth, it followeth it: it ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth and ſhutteth it ſelfe at the riſing and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the ſunne, according to his aſcending or deſcending. This godly Queene choſe this kind of ſimbole, that ſhe might euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſe, how that ſhe referred all her co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations, affections, vowes, words &amp; deedes to almightie God, onely wiſe, and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, as one that meditated vpon heauenly things with all her heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:20154:30"/>
               <head>Antè ferit, quam flamma micet. The flint is ſent before to yeeld fire.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Philip duke of Burgundie vſed this enſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of a flint ſtone ſtriking fire, which ſignifie the difficultie of warres amongſt Kings an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Princes, whereby it commeth to paſſe ofte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> times that the one is conſumed, ouerthrown and vanquiſhed of the other: whereupon fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth calamitie, great loſſes, and a heape dangers on euerie ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:20154:30"/>
               <head>Pretium non vile laborum. He reaped no ſmall reward of his labors.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>In the yeare after the birth of Chriſt, 1429.<note place="margin">Paul. Aemil.</note>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:20154:31"/>the companie of the order of the knights of the Garter, began by the ſame Philip duke of Burgundy, hauing purchaſed a moſt maieſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call name by the donation of the golden fleece. After this he choſe foure and twentie noble men of tried fidelitie to be of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of this honorable ſocietie, adorning them with a chaine of gold, wherein was the flint ſtone burning thoroughout the whole chain, and the golden fleece hanging before the breaſt: imitating herein (as may be ſuppoſed) the marinal expedition of Iaſon into Colchos by diligent obſeruation as it were, of his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and godlines, whereof he was ſaid to be ſo deſirous, that he deſerued the name of good, and the praiſe of an excellent wit, the order wherof his Epitaph which alſo ſheweth the inuention of the golden fleece, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in theſe words.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>I to thintent the church might be,</l>
                  <l>both ſafe and ſure likewiſe,</l>
                  <l>From tyrants rage, inuented haue</l>
                  <l>the goodly golden fleeſe.</l>
               </q>
               <p>There were admitted into the number or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie of theſe knights, next after the Duke himſelfe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>William of Vienna, Lord of ſaint George.</item>
                  <item>Renatus Pottius Lord of Roch.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:20154:31"/>Lord Remblai.</item>
                  <item>Lord of Montague.</item>
                  <item>Roland Huquerquius.</item>
                  <item>Antonie Virgius Earle of Dammartine.</item>
                  <item>Dauid Brimeus, Lord of Lignie.</item>
                  <item>Hugo Launoy, Lord of Santes.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Earle of Cominie.</item>
                  <item>Antonie Thoulongeon marſhall of Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</item>
                  <item>Peter Luxenburg, Earle of Conuerſan.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Trimoille, Lord of Ionuelle.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Luxenburg, Lord of Beaureuoir.</item>
                  <item>Gilbert Launoy, Lord of Villeruall.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Villiers, Lord of Iſleadam.</item>
                  <item>Antonic Lord of Croy, and Renty.</item>
                  <item>Florimundus Brimeus, Lord of Maſſincourt.</item>
                  <item>Robert Lord of Mamines.</item>
                  <item>Iames Brimeu, Lord of Grignie.</item>
                  <item>Baldwin Launey, Lord of Molembaeſius.</item>
                  <item>Peter Baufremontanus, Lord of Chargny.</item>
                  <item>Philip Lord of Teruant.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Crequius.</item>
                  <item>Iohn Croy, Lord of Tours on Marne.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:20154:32"/>
               <head>Flammeſcit vterque. Both of them do burne.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Two Lawrell boughes rubbed hard togither (if we ſhal credite what Plinie hath recorded yeeld fire forth by long and continuall cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Manie are of opinion alſo, that the bone of a Lion do the ſame. So likewiſe moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20154:32"/>it is, that no little danger falleth our, when mightie men meete togither, that the old prouerbe may be verified which ſaith, <hi>Dura duris non quadrare,</hi> in plowing or tilling of the ground, hard things agree not togither. The deſcription of this ſinibole or figure appertaineth to the croſſe of ſaint An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew, as they terme it, and the houſe of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundie were wont to vſe the ſame in their martiall enſignes, when they marched for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and were now come to encounter with their enimies: albeit in euery point they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted not the like ſignification.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:20154:33"/>
               <head>Sara à chi tocca. Whom it happeneth vnto.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The ire of a Prince is ful of preſent danger, as a man may learne by the example of an earthen pot, being now burning on the fire, which if it ſhould chance to fall, it is vnpoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble but that it ſhould do ſome great harme to the ſtanders by. This portraiture or figure, did Iohn duke of Burbon vſe, as by obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we may ſee in moſt places of his countrey of Burbon, &amp; of Elentheropola, or of a village y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the frenchmen inhabited called Beauiolois.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:20154:33"/>
               <head>Nil pennaſed vſus. The fethers are of no force, but vſe-</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>If you marke well the monſtrous bird cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an Oſtrich,<note place="margin">S. Georg.</note> you ſee how with great prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and oſtentation of her feathers, ſhe endeuours to take a great flight, and yet for al that is not an inch higher from the ground when ſhee hath done all that ſhee can:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20154:34"/>The verie like propertie the hypocrites haue, which outwardly make a gay gliſtering ſhew of a zealous holines of religion, but let them once lay away their diſſembling, and then ſearch them thorowly, and you ſhall finde them euen ſtone cold within, &amp; all the often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that they made outwardly to be lies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:20154:34"/>
               <head>Humentia ſiccis. Moiſt things and drie agree not togither.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:20154:35"/>The Enſigne that Galeaz vicechance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, the ſecond Duke of Millan was wont to vſe, may be verified of thoſe which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the prouerbe, are ſaid to carrie fire in the one hand, and water in the other. It was a burning firebrand or a ſtaffe hardned in the fire, with two veſſels ful of water, aboue and beneath. It may haue alſo an other ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, if we more deepely waigh it: namely, that the paſſions of a mans minde are by Gods goodneſſe extinguiſhed by the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of reaſon. Moreouer, by it the ſame dukes magnanimitie is ſignified, for he in a fough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten combat, moſt renowmedly vanquiſhed a Dutch Lord that at that time bore no ſmal countenance, who was the firſt man that vſed the ſame embleme or picture, and chalenged this his Enſigne to himſelfe for a monument of victorie, and for a token of triumph that he got ouer his enimie, who then was put to the worſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:20154:35"/>
               <head>Sola viteit in illo. She onely liued in him.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:20154:36"/>The goddeſſe called Diana Pictanienſis a noble woman, of verie great godlines, and the moſt famous Dutcheſſe of the citie of Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, conceiued a verie conſtant hope touching the reſurrection of the dead, which commeth by death, in our remouing into an other life, who alſo by conſideration of the ſaints in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen oftentimes comforted her ſelfe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is moſt like that by this picture ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured to expreſſe her godly affections: for there is (as you may ſee here) a ſepulchre, and out of it a ſhining dart beutified with greene boughes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:20154:36"/>
               <head>Restat ex victore Orientis. That onely reſteth of all his victories in the Eaſt.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:20154:37"/>What time Philip ſurnamed Auguſtus was king of France,<note place="margin">Of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrelet.</note> Saladinus Sultanus king of Babilon, of Damaſcus, and of Egypt, lay at the point of death at Aſcalon, he appointed that as ſoone as he was dead, his ſhirt ſhould be carried by his ſteward thorough out all the cittie of Aſcalon, hauing a ſpeare thruſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the middle of it, &amp; that the cryer ſhould with a loud voice proclaime as followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>He that of late the mightie raines,</l>
                  <l>of Eaſt did rule at will,</l>
                  <l>Now dead doth onely this conuey,</l>
                  <l>into the darkiſh hell.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Let euerie mightie man take this for a moſt infallible token, that when death comes, he ſpareth neither king nor Caeſar, and that he ſhall depart out of this world, as naked as the pooreſt and vileſt creature doth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:20154:37"/>
               <head>Autor ego audendi. I am the author of being bold.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:20154:38"/>This flaming ſword that Carolus Borboni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, the Cardinall vſed for his enſigne vnder the title of ſaint Andrew, ſignifieth the true ſword of the gouernors of the church, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the holy ghoſt,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> which ſword as Paul ſaith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth the word of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:20154:38"/>
               <head>Non quae ſuper terram. Not thoſe things which are vpon the earth.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:20154:39"/>The food of the ſpirite is that heauenly bread,<note place="margin">Exod. 16</note> or the ſacrament of the bodie &amp; blood of Chriſt, prefigured vnder the tipe of Manna which in former age was ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt downe from heauen to be meate to the Iſraelites. This ſigne or ſimbole the Cardinall of Turnon vſeth at this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:20154:39"/>
               <head>Ab inſomni non cuſtodita Dracone. The golden apples were not kept of the vigilant Dragon.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>It was to ſmall purpoſe or none at all that the Dragon watched ſo carefully for Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, neuertheleſſe came and ſtole away the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20154:40"/>golden apples, that were in the garden of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperus three daughters: By the which is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, that vertues, and famous exploits are euerie where to be found. The ſame effigie the Cardinall of Ferrara vſeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Non quàm diu, ſed quàm benè. It forceth not how long a thing be in doing but how well it be done.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt part of men hold opinion that Thomas of Aquine inuented the Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call knife, but by continuall obſeruation of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20154:40"/>the planets was made ſo perfite thorow the vertue and force thereof, that it cut a thicke and hard Anuell, euen in the middeſt. By this we muſt vnderſtand, that in performing of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny matter whatſoeuer as it ſhould be, we muſt not reſpect the long tract of time that we ſpend in it, ſo that by line and leuill, as they ſay, we finiſh all our actions. Whereupon Suetonius recordeth that Auguſtus Caeſar vſed this prouerbe: <hi>Sat citò, ſi ſat bene,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sueton.</note> which is, any thing is done ſoone enough, if it be done well enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:20154:41"/>
               <head>Quà Proceres abiere pii. Which way our godly forefathers haue gone.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>We reade in holy ſcripture that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Elias was caried thorow the aire in body<note place="margin">King. 2.</note>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:20154:41"/>and ſoule in a firie chariot. By the ſame Metaphor, true and vnfained worſhippers aſcend euen vnto the heauens in ſpirite and feruent meditation, and that is the cauſe wherefore we are perſwaded that the mindes and ſoules of godly men and women are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched, &amp; recreated with great and heauenly conſolations.<note place="margin">Ouid.</note> Hereunto alſo alludeth the Poet Ouid, when he maketh mention of Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras vpon theſe words.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>To God in minde he had acceſſe.</l>
                  <l>And looke what nature hid,</l>
                  <l>From fleſhly eyes, the ſame with ſight,</l>
                  <l>Of heart he hath eſpied.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:20154:42"/>
               <head>Hoc Latio reſtare canunt. Men ſay that this is yet extant in Rome</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:20154:42"/>When the Romaine Conſuls went abroad there were certaine men appointed to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them adorned with triumphant crownes,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> and garlands, and with bundles of yong and tender rods, hauing two Pollaxes in their hands, ſignifying by this ſpectacle the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes of that moſt noble region of Italie, and the whole gouernment of the world, and alſo that the Romaines by their great wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, peace, and affection to the common weale, purchaſed to themſelues no litle praiſe and dignitie. But the iron wreathes, &amp; chaines which you ſee holding the ſpeares, and ſtaues that they cannot fall one from another, doe ſignifie the bondage and captiuity wherewith from that time to this day, Italy is brought to ruine by the wickednes of ſedition and ciuill diſſention.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:20154:43"/>
               <head>Arbitrii mihi iuramei. The raine of will is in my owne hands.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The ancient Alanes,<note place="margin">Meho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius.</note> Burgundians, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sueuians vſed (as Methodius recordeth) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> carrie before them in their martiall enſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a car, which cannot by any meanes be reſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of her libertie: by which embleme they inſinuated their owne deſire that they had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their will and libertie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:20154:43"/>
               <head>Mihi terra, lacúſque. Both the land and water is my owne.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Such was the eſtimation of Auguſtus Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar towards his friend Maecenas,<note place="margin">Dion.</note> that he committed vnto him the gouernement of his countrey, as well by land as by ſea: wherefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e cauſed the ſhape of a frogge to be drawne for his cognizance. Except peraduenture he would ſignifie thoſe frogs in Syriphie, which (as Plinie ſaith) are mute, and without voice;<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or ſo it may repreſent a cloſe and hidden ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and alſo a faithfull concealing of things commited to ones fidelitie. Which vertue this Maecenas ſo practiſed that Auguſtus Caeſar himſelfe for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cauſe highly reuerenced him,<note place="margin">Eutrop.</note> &amp; had him in great admiration for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hatred that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:20154:44"/>he bore them that vſed enuiouſlie to giue pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie ſcoffes and taunts vnder pretence of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained friendſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>ΦΩΣ ΦΕΡΟΙ ΗΔΕ ΤАΛΗΝΗΝ. The raine bow doth bring faire weather.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt faire and bountifull queene of France Katherine, vſed the ſigne of the raine bow for her armes, which is an infallible ſigne of peaceable calmenes, and tranquillitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:20154:44"/>
               <head>Vltorem vlciſcitur vltor. The reuenge lighteth vpon the reuenger.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Charles the ſixt of that name, king of France,<note place="margin">Froſſard.</note> whileſt he ſought the ſatiffying of his
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20154:45"/>owne wilfulnes, in going about to reuenge his friend Oliuerius Cliffonius his conſtable<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe againſt one Peter Craonius, had a very infortunate end, as it was foretold him: the which thing doth moſt certainely fall out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as many as runne headlong to reuenge, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially other mens cauſes. It chanced tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he leuied an armie to go into the prouinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Britones, to the intent he might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> reuenged of the Lieutenant there becauſe he ſeemed to defend Petrus Craonius cauſe And ſo as he was going thorow the forreſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thicket of the Manſenſians or Caenonians, there met him in the middle betwixt tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> trees a certaine ſtrange man, pretending great pouertie &amp; need, and taking the king<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> horſe by the bridle, cauſed him to ſtay, &amp; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with loud voice ſaid vnto him: Oh king, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thou wilt follow my counſaile go no furthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> forward, but rather turne backe againe, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there are of thy owne armie that haue ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thee into thy enimies hands. When the king heard theſe words, he was maruellouſly terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, &amp; ſo moued withall, that he was as pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as aſhes (as they ſay) with fear, &amp; with horro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thereof did euen grate with his teeth as it were, and as ill happe was, he was a very yong man, and therefore vnſkilfull of matial fears
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20154:45"/>beſides he had a bodie of ſuch a conſtitution that it was alwayes ſubiect to ſickneſſe and agues. But when the captaines of his armie ſaw him in that caſe, they labored to eſtabliſh and confirme his minde, that yet was doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful what was beſt to be done, and ſo they went boldly forward. They were no ſooner gon out of the wood, but two of the kings pages were hard at their horſe heeles, puffing and blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as comming about ſome waightie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whereof the one ware the kings helmet, and the other a common ſouldiers ſpeare. It chanced that whileſt the one of them ſlept, the king ſpeare fell out of his hand vpon his head which ware the helmet. The king hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a ſodaine noiſe, and looking aſide, ſaw a man at his heeles, whom as yet he know not, ſo he was maruellouſty troubled, and in a great rage leaped downe from his horſe, and as one that had bene beſides himſelfe, drew his ſword, and neither regarding the order of his owne men, neither vſing the aduiſe of reaſon, laid about him as if he had bene in the thickeſt of his enimies, vſing theſe words: Beſtirre you, play the men, &amp; diſpatch me theſe traitors. When the kings pages heard him ſay ſo, they made all the haſt they could to ſaue their liues, by running away.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20154:46"/>But the kings own brother who was captain of the Aurelians, riding by the kings ſide, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the brunt of his furie: for the king ſo forcib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranne vpon him with his naked ſword in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hand, that had not the Duke ſpeedily fled<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> away, he had bene in danger of his life. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the laſt the king was euen tyred with labo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and the horſe wearied with many and gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> courſes that he made, it chanced that onc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the kings horſemen met him, and by fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> meanes brought both the king and his ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> backe to the Caemonians. But the king was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mad and ſo angrie in his minde, that who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſaw him thought he would neuer recoue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And ſo it fel out that there was an end of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> intended voyage, and the armie broke vp, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> returned. But after that the king came ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to his palace, he became far weaker than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had bene, and was ſo ſubiect to a ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of phrenſie, that ſometimes would leaue h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and then come to him againe, that he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> brought to great miſerie and extremitie the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by. Yea the beſt thing that he got by that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> happie voyage, was a verie great miſhap a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> euill fortune that chanced to his whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. for euen to this day it feeleth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wounds and bruſes of ſo great a calamitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:20154:46"/>
               <head>Colligauit nemo. Hitherto no man hath conquered me.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>There is vſed to this day certaine braſen money with the image of Auguſtus Caeſar on it, vpon the one ſide wherof is the portraiture
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:20154:47"/>of a Crocodile chained faſt to a palme tree, with this inſcription: Col. Nem. which is, No man hath euer bound me before. By which ſigne Caeſar would ſignifie that none before him did euer ſubdue Egypt, and triumphed ouer it. For the Crocodile repreſenteth Egipt, which is to be found onely in the riuer Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, by the commodie whereof all Egypt is made fruitfull. Beſides the Crocodile is faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Palme tree, that thereby the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders might be admoniſhed that the godly Prince Auguſtus triumphed ouer all Egypt, by getting of which victorie and peace, he was recreated and refreſhed, as a drie and thirſtie ground is with a ſhowre of raine. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, this ſimbole ſignifieth that Auguſtus got the victorie, and preuailed againſt Auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, and Cleopatra of famous memorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:20154:47"/>
               <head>Latet anguis in herba. The adder lurketh priuilie in the graſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:20154:48"/>In gathering of flowers, and ſtrawberies that grow low vpon the ground, we muſt be verie carefull for the adder and ſnake that lieth lurking in the graſſe, for looke whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhe ſtingeth, they hardly recouer after. So in reading of authors, and bookes, which carrie a faire ſhew to the eye, and yeelding ſmall delight to the eare, we muſt be carefull that we runne not into abſurd, and wrong iudgements, and opinions, &amp; by that meanes make ſhipwracke of our ſoules.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:20154:48"/>
               <head>Labuntur nitidis, ſcabriſque tenatiùs haerent. Flies do fall downe from ſlipperie place, but ſtick faſt vpon the hard and rough.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:20154:49"/>As flies cannot ſtay themſelues on ſlippery places,<note place="margin">Plutar.</note> as vpon glaſſe and ſuch like, but fall downe, whereas they reſt well vpon ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as be rough and hollow, ſo it fareth with vs when we are in proſperitie and haue all things at will, we vſe quickly to fall into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe and ſundrie ſinnes: whereas on the otherſide being touched ſometimes with croſſes and afflictions, we ſtay our ſelues in ſome meaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:20154:49"/>
               <head>Teſtante, virebo. While thou ſtandeſt I ſhall floriſh.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>As y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cardinall of Lorraine ſhould lately en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his Abbey of Clunie, his armies were
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:20154:50"/>ſet vp before the gates of the houſe, to wit, a great foure ſquared piller, brode beneath, &amp; ſharpe on the toppe, hauing on the higher end the new moone blaſed, and from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome vpward compaſſed about with greene berries, and garniſhed with theſe verſes, which were engrauen round about.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>O Reader tell what thing is ment,<note place="margin">Ouid.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>By tombes in Memphis towne,</l>
                  <l>Which on the top doth beare on high</l>
                  <l>The bright beames of the moone?</l>
                  <l>The moone which doth continually,</l>
                  <l>Increaſe in light ſo bright,</l>
                  <l>Till that night come wherin her ſhine,</l>
                  <l>From world doth take her flight.</l>
                  <l>And what doth meane the ſacred Iuy,</l>
                  <l>Which creepes and binds about,</l>
                  <l>This tomb, to whoſe high top he climbs</l>
                  <l>Although it be full ſtout.</l>
                  <l>And what new faſhion is this alſo,</l>
                  <l>That leaning to it ſtickes,</l>
                  <l>Making his ſtay about the ſame,</l>
                  <l>That greenely ouer creepes.</l>
                  <l>This tombe it is that mightie king,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe maieſtie honor craues,</l>
                  <l>For he in heauen triumphes for vs,</l>
                  <l>To ſathan that were ſlaues.</l>
                  <l>And the Iuie a biſhop ſignifies,</l>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:20154:50"/>
                  <l>Euen thee moſt famous prince,</l>
                  <l>Who in a godly life doeſt yeeld,</l>
                  <l>Not to the beſt an inch.</l>
                  <l>For though thy bodie lie in graue,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſuch thy vertue was,</l>
                  <l>That it beares vp our laud and praiſe,</l>
                  <l>That neuer away ſhall paſſe.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:20154:51"/>
               <head>Inter eclipſes exorior. I ſhine in the darke.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>That great and mightie cup of gold of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> princely Dolphin, ſeemeth to me to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:20154:51"/>that ancient ſtanding peece of Apolloes Rauen, whom the Poets do faine to be placed amongſt the ſtarres: but the inſcription, or apothegme which is written aboue it, may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be drawne to his happie birth day. And ſuch is the interpretation that Paradinus gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth of it. But in my iudgement he would thereby allude to his fathers interpretation, which is, <hi>Donec totum impleat orbem,</hi> vntill he fulfill the whole compaſſe of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:20154:52"/>
               <head>Fiducia concors. We truſt or hope all one thing.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:20154:52"/>There was alwayes carried before the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Romaines, ſtandards which had the palme of a hand blaſed after this faſhion: you may ſee the ſame alſo in diuerſe other places in auncient coynes, and money, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n other famous monuments of like antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Therefore this ancient ſigne doth beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the benefite, or hand of concord, the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture wherof is to be ſeene in the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the commentaries of the Romaine common welth, which Wolfangus Lazius, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iligent ſearcher out of antiquities, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of Romaines Phiſitian, and a verie cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing hiſtoriagrapher. beſides lately penned, and ſet forth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:20154:53"/>
               <head>Scilicet is ſuperis labor est. A high matter in a loe houſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:20154:53"/>Not farre from the gates of Leontychidas houſe, ſenator of the Lacedemonians, there was a liue ſerpent or ſnake, that had wrapped himſelfe about the Key of a locke. When this came to the ſouthſayers cares, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly affirmed before him that it ſignified ſome ſtrange wonder that ſhould happen. To whom he thus replied. Surely to me it ſeemes a thing of no great wonder, if the ſnake haue wrapped himſelfe about the Key: but rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the contratie part, if the Key had folded it ſelfe about the ſerpent, then without all doubt, it had bene a thing to be wondred at. And ſo the wiſe Senator making but a ieſt of it, laughed at their fooliſh ſuperſtition. And ſurely at this day, the common peoples cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie is verie much infected, about manie things which happen ſometimes after an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie manner, yet by as naturall meanes as may be, yea, when they are I ſay: if you thorowly examine them plainly agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to nature. In fine, there is likewiſe a prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous iudgement or inconſtancie touching matters of faith in theſe and the like ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions, which with wicked traditions bring no ſmall corruption to mans iudgement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:20154:54"/>
               <head>Horrent con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>moueri. Things that are fearce of nature are not to be prouoked.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The crueltie of the beare being angred to chafed, is not in any ſort to be prouoked, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> moued, like as the minde of a man is not to be incenſed when he is throughly angred for there we may looke for nothing elſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him, but great and deadly danger.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:20154:54"/>
               <head>Si ſciens fallo. Euill come to me if I deceiue wittingly.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The Romaines when they ſhould giue ouer their warres,<note place="margin">Fl. Blond.</note> and make peace with their eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, vſed theſe ceremonies, that he who had authoritie giuen him to deale with the enimy
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:20154:55"/>in the behalfe of the reſt in thoſe matters, ſhould take a flint or ſome other ſtone in his hand, and hit a pigge, or hogge therewith, pronouncing at that inſtant this ſentence: Looke what happeneth to this pigge that you ſee here, happen vnto me if I deceiue you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:20154:55"/>
               <head>Inuitum fortuna fouet. Fortune when he fauneth, heapeth too much vpon a man.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Policrates king of the Samions had ſuch ſucceſſe with ſuch perſeuerance in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous-waies of ſmiling fortune,<note place="margin">Strabo.</note> that once he went about either to diminiſh it, or elſe to change it: namely, by caſting a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie rich ring into the middeſt of the ſea, the which for all that, was found after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward-in the belly of a fiſh, which the fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men amongſt the reſt had caught. But marke
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:20154:56"/>what came of it. Not long after the king of the Perſians chanced to take this king, and being apprehended, commanded him to be hanged, and miſerably to be ſtrangled. So thus you may ſee that the flattering faunings of fortune (which the world compteth great felicitie in this life) are neither certaine not conſtant, nor of any continuance: and the more glorious and glittering they appeare, the more eaſily and ſpeedilie they vaniſh away, like a glaſſe, which of it owne nature is brickle and fraile.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:20154:56"/>
               <head>Ecquis emat tanti ſeſe dimittere? Will any man buy ſo deare, that which is ſo full of all kind of cares.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Valerius Maximus maketh mention of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain king,<note place="margin">Val. Max. li. 7. ca. 2.</note> who when there was a rich Diadem offered vnto him, pauſed a while before he would put it on his head, &amp; ſtudying as it were what were beſt to do, burſt forth into theſe words, Oh more noble, then happie orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for if a man knew thorowly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> how many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, perrils, &amp; miſeries it is ſtuffed, he would not take it vp from the ground to haue it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:20154:57"/>
               <head>Comminus quo minus. How much the leſſet, ſo much the neerer.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:20154:57"/>When a certaine Lacedemonian was on a time noted of cowardlyneſſe, becauſe he had cauſed a flie to be printed on his target, and ſuch a one as did not exceed to the common ſort of that kinde in bigneſſe, as though he ſhould hereby ſignifie, that he would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuey himſelfe out of the battaile, and like a fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e would not be ſeene of his enimie, he anſwered, nay rather, I encounter with my enimie hand to hand, and ſo ſet vpon him, that albeit the ſigne be ſmall, yet the enimie may well diſcerne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:20154:58"/>
               <head>Transfundit pasta venenum. The Waſpes after they haue fed of the ſerpent, powre out their poiſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Some there are in the world ſo wickedly bent, &amp; of ſuch a deſpighfull nature, that they are maruellouſly delighted in gathering togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all kind of deadly calumnies y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> poiſoned tongues can vtter, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> afterwards if any chance to be purſued by them, they ſting him ſore, &amp; if they may by any meanes, they wil bring him to his graue with ſorrow. Wherein they imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the waſpes, which feeding vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſerpent with great greedines, make their ſtings more venimous, and therfore the wounds receiued by them are the more perillous &amp; dangerous.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:20154:58"/>
               <head>Celſa potestatis ſpecies. A ſpeciall marke or token of his authoritie and power.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:20154:59"/>Vpon the ſignet of Pompeius Magnus which he wore vpon his finger (whereon Iuliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar when he was killed hapning to fall,<note place="margin">Plutar.</note> being brought to him by one of his ſouldiers, wept bitterly) there was (as Plutarch writeth) the ſhape of a Lion ſhaking a ſword betweene his forefeete ingrauen, to ſignifie perhaps a hard and bold voyage or enterpriſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Proſtibuli eligantia. The coyneſſe of a whore.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Salomon the wiſe in his Prouerbs, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the honor of a ſhameleſſe and common woman,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rouer. 11</note> to a pigge wearing a gold ring in her ſnowte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:20154:59"/>
               <head>Ardua deturbans vis animoſa quatit. Bold force doth ouercome high things.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>To ouercome difficult and hard things there is need of great induſtrie, labor, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, as may appeare by the example of the Egle, for when ſhe goeth to ſet vpon the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt, ſhe lighteth downe vpon his hornes, and there fluttereth vp and downe, and ſo filleth his eyes with duſt (which ſhe had heaped to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither before in her feathers for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) that at the laſt he caſteth himſelf downe headlong,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> from ſome high rocke, or hill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:20154:60"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ias tuas domme demonstra mibi. Lord teach me thy pathes.<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.</note>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Vpon the fourth veſſel of that kind which had three ranks of Ores in it, which Andreas Darius admirall of the Empire, commanded to be made for the Emperor againſt he ſhould go to Tunetum, there was placed the ſhape
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:20154:60"/>or forme of a blaſing ſtarre glittering on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſide with arrowes as it were in faſhion of a round circle, for a continuall admonition to implore and call for Gods direction and mightie arme in this his voyage and iourney.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:20154:61"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nica ſemper auis. But alwayes one Phenix in the world at once.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Like as the Phenix wherof there is but one at any time to be ſeene,<note place="margin">Theoph.</note> is a rare bird, ſo all good &amp; precious things are hard to be found. Theſe armes the famous and renowmed wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dy Helionora of Auſtria vſed, which was the widow of Francis king of France.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:20154:61"/>
               <head>ΑΠΑΑΝΩΣ. Without all falſhood or deceipt.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:20154:62"/>The french arming ſword in the hands of an armed man, with the inſcription of this Greeke word ΑΠΑΑΝΩΣ doth at this day in the place of the armes which the Lord Conſtable vſed, ſignifie faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:20154:62"/>
               <head>Riens ne ́ eſt plus, Plus ne ́ eſt riens. I haue no more ioy, no more comfort remaineth to me.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:20154:63"/>Valentina of Milan, ſometime Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe of Orleans had great cauſe to paſſe her dayes in great heauineſſe and mourning, both for the death of her huſband Lewis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to king Charles the ſixt, as alſo for the ſame kings vnfortunate phrenſie (whereof we ſpake before in the handling of his a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes) which vſed to come on him at certain times, and when it tooke him, he knew not any of his friends, no not the queene his wife, but only this Dutcheſſe Valentina, whom he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led when he was in this extremitie his ſiſter. Whereupon there was a rumour blowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode that the Duke the father of this Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina, hauing ſometimes bene ouerladen with drinke, had cauſed ſome poyſon, or charmed potion to be giuen him: which report this Valentina tooke verie grieuouſly, yea ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly indeede, that in place of all conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and eaſe of her mourning, ſhe vſed for her cognizance an earthen pitcher in faſhion like a water pot, on the mouth whereof was the character of this letter S. ſignifying perhaps theſe words concerning the ſame Dutches: <hi>Sola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaepe ſeſeipſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſollicitari, ſuſpiraré<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>,</hi> that is, being alone ſhee accuſtomed to mourne and to ſigh with her ſelfe, togither with theſe words ſubioyned. <hi>Nil mihi prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea:
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:20154:63"/>Praeterea mihi nil</hi> Which is, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing remaineth to me, nothing haue I more. The which emblemes with the like inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are to be ſeene deſcribed in many places in the Franciſcan friers church at Bloyes, and in the ſame Dutches chappell, where ſhe lieth buried in a tombe of braſſe, and alſo in the porch or entrie on euery ſide of the quite of the ſame church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:20154:64"/>
               <head>Pour vn aultre non. To none other.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:20154:64"/>Andreas Lauallus the french Admiral, was wont to giue for his enſigne, a burning Ore, which is yet to be ſeene in the ſuburbes of the cittie Melus. It is alſo a ſignification of feruent and dutifull zeale, towards the king and countrie, and eſpecially in that iourney that they tooke by ſea through the great Occean.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:20154:65"/>
               <head>Fata viam inuenient. Fortune ſhall ſhew the way.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>This ſimbole of the Labirinth, which the Lord of Boiſdaulphin, archbiſhop of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brune vſeth, may perchance ſignifie, that we are lead by the grace of God to finde the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:20154:65"/>way that leadeth to eternall life, the ſame giuing the thread as it were of his holy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts into our hands, which when we haue once taken hold of, and do follow, we turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the dangerous wandrings, and feareful by wayes of this world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Quid non mortalia pectora cogis? Filthy loue conſtraineth men to commit all wickedneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Cleopatra taking it grieuouſly,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> and alſo in great diſdaine that Marcus Antonius ſhould make triall ſo oft of her loue, vpon a time
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:20154:66"/>at a banquet and merrie meeting, whether it were to giue him occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer to be diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full any more after, or for ſome other cauſe, ſhe began to delight him verie voluptuouſly, after her old faſhion that ſhe vſed: namely, with diuers and ſundrie garlands of flowers, whoſe leaues were all beſprinckled with poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Some of the which ſhe wearing vpon her head, picked them out and bruſing them a little, caſt them into his cuppe or goblet, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading him to drinke it off. But whileſt he was about to do it, ſhe putting her hand to it, ſaid thus, Oh my ſweete heart Antonius, I ſurely am the woman, which if I could liue without thee, haue now a iuſt occaſion to do that, which by your curious trials you ſeeme to feare. And hereby we may ſee what may be the audacitie, and impudent boldnes of a ſhameleſſe woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:20154:66"/>
               <head>In ſibilo aurae tenuis. In the muttering of the gentle aire.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:20154:67"/>Muſicke is of it owne nature an enimie to melancholy, and therefore is able to qualifie any furie that riſeth of a vehement melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholie. Wherefore ſhe is able alſo to driue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way heauines, and dulneſſe, which proceed of blacke choler, being ouerwhelmed and ſuffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with flegme. With the which one hath recorded that once he ſaw a man ſore trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and ſo ſound and faſt on ſteepe, that you could by no meanes get a word of him, but onely by a harpe ſounding in his eares, at the pleaſant harmonie whereof, he lifting vp his head, laughed, &amp; anſwered to their demands. Which thing is an argument that there is no ſmall affinitie betwixt Muſicke and the ſoule. Elizeus the prophet hath plainely declared the ſame vnto vs,<note place="margin">4. King. 2</note> when to call againe his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall ſpirite, and to make ſupplication to God for a remedie of his people that then were like to periſh with extreme thirſt, he commanded one that had ſkill to play on the harpe to be called for vnto him, and in that ſort obtained at the hands of God that which he deſired in his prayers, and ſupplications. And what ſay you to Dauid the Muſitian, who is now dead &amp; rotten?<note place="margin">1. King. 17</note> Did not he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and recreate King Saul, his ſoule being vexed with an euill ſpirite, when as, ſo long as
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:20154:67"/>he played vpon his harpe, the wicked ſpirite left to moleſt him. Therefore this conſonant muſicke hath a certaine diuine grace in it, for as much as it doth not onely reſtore helth to bodies that are ſicke, but al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reth vp the ſoule to contemplation, comforteth the ſame, and maketh it heauenly as it were: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is an enimie euen to the verie diuels, which doubtleſſe are nothing elſe than deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, deiection of the ſoule, feare, and an obſtinate deſolation. Finally, as in Muſicke of different voices there is made tunable mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, ſo of men alſo that are of one minde there may be made a conſent of contrary na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and manners, which God accepteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other things that may be obſerued or kept.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20154:68"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20154:68"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:20154:87"/>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Finem tranſcendit habendi. He paſſed the ordinarie meanes of getting and poſſeſſing riches.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The wicked couetouſneſſe of Calephas Baldacenſis chiefe biſhop of the Mahomets law, wrought a verie euil end for himſelfe: for being taken in wars, Haalon prince of Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, commanded him to be handled accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to bis inſaciable greedineſſe: that is, that inſteede of his daintie diſhes nothing ſhould be ſet before him, but platters and other great veſſels full of gold, and as oft as theſe things ſhould be brought before him, his miniſters ſhould deride and ſcoffe at him with theſe words, Take, eate that which thou haſt alwayes deſired, and loued, take and fill thy belly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:20154:87"/>
               <head>Heu cadit in quemquam tantum ſcelus. Did euer like puniſhment light vpon any.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:20154:88"/>
                  <note place="margin">Coelius.</note>Thus the young innocent virgins ſuffered ſore puniſhment for the wicked factes that their father Dioniſius Siracuſanus Tyrannus the younger had committed. For the Locri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans when they had driuen their father Dioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius out of the kingdome, reuenging his cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for the deflowring of their citizens daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and wiues, permitted his daughters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet yong tender virgins to be rauiſhed of as many as woulde: and at the laſt, hauing no regard of their innocencie, but with a barbarous and ſauage crueltie, purſued them to death, by d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iuing ſharpe needles, or pinnes vnder the nayles of their fingers, with ſo great paine, and torment, as neuer before, nor ſince was heard of the like.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:20154:88"/>
               <head>Preſſa est inſignis gloria facti. The glorie of his noble deede is recorded in writing.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:20154:89"/>Iulian the Apoſtata ſometimes Emperor of Nicomedia made a publike decree, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Chriſtians the vſe of ſchooles, and al adminiſtration, or gouernement in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth, which S. Iohn the Martyr percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to be ioyned with the deſtruction of Chriſtian religion more then any kind of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie, or puniſhment that could be deuiſed, openly pulled it in peeces, and tore it. By which action of his we are taught that there ought to be no threatning of mans inuention be it neuer ſo great, ſo fearefull, that it ſhould conſtraine or make our conſcience to ſhrinke or diſſemble any thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:20154:89"/>
               <head>Cedo nulli. I giue place to none.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Eraſmus Roterodamus vſed for his ſim.<note place="margin">T. Liuius.</note> bole the image of Terminus the God of the Romanes, which neuer gaue place to Iupiter himſelfe, for the which thing Caruayalus a Franciſcan frier found fault with him. Laying
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:20154:69"/>it to his charge, and obiecting it as a thing done too arrogantly of Eraſmus, for that he thereby ſignified that he woulde yeelde to no man on earth in anie point of learning: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that ſentence indeede may be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode of death which is the laſt or vttermoſt bond or limite of all things, which no man is able, or by anie meanes may eſcape, or flie from: with the which anſwere Caruayalus was ſatilfied and contented.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:20154:69"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <p>
                        <hi>En altera quae vehat Argo.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>There was in ancient time a nation of the Franques,<note place="margin">L. Paca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. S. Apolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natis. B. Rena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> or French that were verie cunning ſhipwrights, and much exerciſed in that art, if we ſhall beleeue Latinus, Pacatus, Sidonius, Apollinaris, &amp; Beatus Renanus. And it ſemed
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:20154:70"/>good to that nation, that in what region ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they choſe them a place to build them a cittie and to dwell in, the portrature or ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole of a goodly great ſhippe ſhould be dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to the honor of their ſhippes, and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie. The which thing Lutetia in Paris which is incomparable by that famous gift, hath chalenged to it ſelfe by ancient name euen to this day. Neither is it any abſurditie to thinke that they borrowed the ſame cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Gepides which alſo vſed the ſame before,<note place="margin">Method.</note> and were verie famous thorow all the Germaine Ocean: The Troian nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on perchance comming thither from their long voyage on the ſea, after the ſubuerſion of Troy, from whom it is thought of the moſt part, the nobilitie of France tooke their beginning and originall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:20154:70"/>
               <head>Insperatum auxilium. Helpe vnlooked for.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Marcus Valerius a Romaine,<note place="margin">T. Liuius Plinie. A. Gelliu</note> fighting a combate on a time hand to hand with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine aduerſarie of his, named Gallus, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him by the aid that he had vnlooked for. For it chanced that a rauen houered a prettie while ouer his head peece, and at the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:20154:71"/>laſt lighting on it, ſo pecked and ſmothered his enemies eyes that Valerius at the laſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercame him. Whereupon this Valerius was named of the ſame rauen Coruinus: although if you reſpect the victorie it ſelfe, he can not chalenge the ſame to him ſelfe by his owne manhood, but by the prouidence of God. Yet neuertheleſſe Auguſtus Ceſar cauſed a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument to be erected to the ſame Coruinus, on the top of whoſe helmet ſat the rauen, for a token of ſo worthie an exploit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:20154:71"/>
               <head>Tutum telittore ſistam. I will ſet thee ſafe vpon the ſhore.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:20154:72"/>We haue referred to this place the ſigne of the anker,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.</note> in token of the hope of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Ieſus Chriſt, who is our moſt certaine and ſure reſuge, and to whom we are to flie In all extremities. True it is, that Seleucusking of Siria vſed the portrature of an anker in his ſignet: but this he did for that cauſe onely, for that the ſouthſayers and wiſe men had told hold him,<note place="margin">Appian.</note> the anker did repreſent or ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his kingdome. Moreouer, Titus the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror vſed the ſame cognizance, but in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect, as afterwards we will declare elſe where. Finally, manie Admirals haue vſed and do to this day vſe the ſame in token (as it ſhould ſeeme) of their office, and authoritie in the common wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:20154:72"/>
               <head>Quò tendis? Whether goeſt thou?</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:20154:73"/>Beſides other diſcommodities which the tongue bringeth with it,<note place="margin">Iames. 3.</note> Saint Iames ſaith the ſame is tipped with poiſon, and bringeth death, comparing it to the ſtearne of a ſhip by which the whole veſſell is ruled and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tterned. Which ſentence agreeth with the opinion of Bias, to whom Amaſis king of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt ſent a whole beaſt on this condition, that he ſhoulde ſende to him againe the beſt and the woorſt peece therof, who ſent the tongue onely. Seeing then that that part of the body is of ſuch great moment, it is no maruel if na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture haue compaſſed it in, with hedges and pales, as it were with double gates, which we muſt neuer vſe to open without the conſent of reaſon and wiſedome going before, elſe, where the tongue goeth before premeditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the entrance into theſe gates is a fearefull thing, &amp; the going out both dangerous, and vnfortunate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:20154:73"/>
               <head>Putreſcet Iugum. The yoke of bondage ſhall rot away.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The prophet Eſaie propheſying that the freedome of the ſpirite ſhoulde bee reſtored by the comming of Chriſt, ſaith,<note place="margin">Eſay. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Computre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcet iugum à facie olei,</hi> that is, al bondage or ſe ruitude ſhal flie away before the annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lorde, which is Chriſt, by whome the children of God increaſing and going forward in the loue of God, &amp; the obedience of his commandements ſhalbe releaſed &amp; ſet free from the ſeruile bondage and yoke of
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:20154:74"/>the law. For in this ſpirituall Iubiley the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie are abſolued from their ſinnes, and their debts are pardoned, the proſcript and bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed are permitted to returne to their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, their inheritance is reſtored them: ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, that is to ſay, thoſe that are ſold vnder ſinne are ſet at libertie, and by the benefite of Ieſus Chriſt, the true oile, and ointmen of mercie, felicitie, and grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:20154:74"/>
               <head>Nec fas est, nec poſſe reor. It is neither law nor can be I ſuppoſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Not whoſoeuer is in bands or priſon,<note place="margin">Actes. 12.</note> but he that is intangled in vices and ſinne, is to be iudged a bondſlaue. For albeit Peter the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle was kept in Herod his priſon, bound with two chaines, yet by the miniſterie of an Angel his chaines fell from his hands, and he eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, paſſing thorow the iron gates, which by the wil of God (which by no mans deuiſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can, nor ought to be impugned) opened of their owne accord, and gaue him paſſage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:20154:75"/>
               <head>Semine ab aethereo. From the heauenly ſeede.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame earth which ſwallowed vp Core, Dathan &amp; Abiron with the reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> troublers of the prieſthood &amp; miniſtery of Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the ſame thing in the Leuitical tribe,<note place="margin">Numb. 16. and 17.</note> and that not without a miſterie, whileſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> amongſt the rods of the Iſraelites erected in the taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:20154:75"/>of the Lord, the ſecond day the rod of Aaron onely budded, &amp; bare fruit or Almons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Ventura deſuper vrbi. To fall vpon the crue.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:20154:76"/>The miſerable deſtruction of Ieruſalem by the Romanes after the paſſion of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioſeph. Egeſipp.</note> was foreſhewed before by manie wonders &amp; ſignes, eſpecially by a firie commet appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in forme of a ſword, and hanging ouer the ſteeple for the ſpace of a whole yeare to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither: ſhewing as it were by this ſigne, that the iuſtice of God would take puniſhment of the wicked nation of the Iewes by fire and blood, for their great impietie and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: which thing not onely came to paſſe, but alſo moſt raging famine tormenting them, there was found one who killed and cate her owne child.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:20154:76"/>
               <head>In vtrumque paratus. Readie to both.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The Iſraelites after their returne from the captiuitie of Babilon,<note place="margin">2. Eſd. 4.</note> taking in the one hand a trowell, in the other a ſword (ſuch were the continuall troubles of their enimies) built vp the wals of Ieruſalem. Which thing in a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie did repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the miniſters of the church of Chriſt, who are bound to inſtruct the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and to bring againe thoſe that do erre in the faith (which are very ruines in deed) &amp; to fight manfully with the ſword of Gods word againſt the enimies thereof, which are vices and ſinne.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20154:77"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20154:77"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20154:78"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20154:78"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:20154:79"/>
               <head>Vindice fato. Deſtenie being reuenger.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Dauid being a little child, but armed with grace from aboue,<note place="margin">2. King. 17</note> feared not to enter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate with the great and fearefull giant Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah: neither would he put on the armor of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:20154:79"/>Saul, but contenting himſelfe with a ſling and fiue flint ſtones, ouerthrew this monſter, and triumphed ouer him. In like manner that we may ouercome that fearefull and dangerous enimie of mankind the diuell, the onely wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of a ſtable faith, firme hope, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant affiance in the merites of Chriſts paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and death are enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:20154:80"/>
               <head>Nil ſolidum. Nothing is firme or continuall in this life.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>At the time of the creation of the biſhops of Rome, when according to the cuſtome, he that is nominate Pope entreth into S. Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries church (wherein many of the Romiſh bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:20154:80"/>are buried, the maſter of the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies goeth before him, carrying in his hands two reedes, tying to the top of the one a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning candle, which flaming he putteth to the other, whereto are tyed hurds, or flaxe, and ſo burneth them both, ſaying theſe words three times togither, Oh holy fathers, ſo paſſeth the glorie of this world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:20154:81"/>
               <head>Vtrum lubet. Whether pleaſeth him.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:20154:81"/>Clubbes, or battes compaſſed about with Oliue branches, being a ſigne as wel of peace,<note place="margin">A. Gelliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as of warre, may be giuen to thoſe, to whom we giue the choiſe as well of the one as of the other. Which thing our anceſters portrayed with a white wand, ſuch as Ambaſſadors vſe to carrie that intreat for peace; and a ſpeare adioyned, as the Romanes did to the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginians, or elſe with two ſpeares, the one whereof had his point tipped with ſteele, the other blunted with a knobbe of wood on the end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:20154:82"/>
               <head>Agere &amp; pati fortiae. To do and ſuffer great things.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:20154:82"/>C. Mutius when in ſteede of Porſena King of the Hetruſcans, who had beſieged Rome,<note place="margin">Liuius lib. 2. Valerius.</note> he had ſlaine the kings ſecretarie, was ſo angrie with himſelfe that he thruſt his right hand into the fire which he had made to ſacrifice withall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:20154:83"/>
               <head>Lex exlex. The law, or ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> law.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:20154:83"/>Anacharſis the Philoſopher compared lawes to cobwebbes,<note place="margin">Valerius the great</note> becauſe they troubled &amp; oppreſſed the little flies, and ſuch ſmall vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, but neuer touched the great ones. Which thing we ſee to be too true in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments now adayes, whileſt the mightie are ſauoured, and the poore and meaner ſort taxed, and ſeuerely handled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:20154:84"/>
               <head>Tutus ab igne ſacer. Being holy I was ſafe from the violence of the fire.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:20154:84"/>
                  <note place="margin">Plutarch. Valerius the great.</note>Lituns being a crooked ſtaffe, whereupon the ſouthſayers ſate when they deuined of things to come, which Romulus vſed inſteede of an Iuorie ſcepter, periſhed not in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the flame at Rome, but was found ſafe and ſound in the middeſt of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:20154:85"/>
               <head>Parce Imperator. Pardon me moſt noble Emperor.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>M. Sceua a moſt valiant knight of Iulius Caeſats,<note place="margin">Appian.</note> in that battaile which he fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Pompey, loſt one of his eyes, and had his body thruſt thorow ſeuen times, his ſhield was found alſo to be pearced with a hundred and twentie darts.<note place="margin">Caeſar.</note> And (as Caeſar himſelfe
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:20154:85"/>reporteth) notwithſtanding that his ſhield was ſtrooke thorow 230. places,<note place="margin">Sueton. Valerius</note> yet he kept the gate ſtill, and the entrance, which he had taken vpon him to defend. And whileſt he went in the foreward of the battell in France and fought hand to hand with his enimies, his hippe being ſore hurt, and his face bruſed with great ſtones, his helmet, and his ſhield broken, and fallen out of his hand, and his ſword ſhiuered in diuerſe peeces, and being armed with a double breſt plate, with great holdneſſe caſt himſelfe into the ſea, and by ſwimming thorow the waters which he had made redde with the bloud of his enimies, he came to his owne men. Whither when he was come, as ſoone as he perceiued himſelfe to be vnarmed, which by the law of armes was forbidden, he cried out to the Prince (for he truſted not yet to ſo many dangers which he had ouercome.) Oh noble Emperour for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue me, I come to thee vnarmed. This was the vertue and manly proweſſe of Sceua, wherefore for a reward, he was preferred to the dignitie of a Centurion.</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:20154:86"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:20154:86"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:20154:90"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:20154:90"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:20154:91"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:20154:91"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:20154:92"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:20154:92"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:20154:93"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:20154:93"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:20154:94"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:20154:94"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:20154:95"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:20154:95"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:20154:96"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:20154:96"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:20154:97"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:20154:97"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:20154:98"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:20154:98"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:20154:99"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:20154:99"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:20154:100"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:20154:100"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:20154:101"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:20154:101"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:20154:102"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:20154:102"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:20154:103"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:20154:103"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:20154:104"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:20154:104"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:20154:105"/>
               <head>Euertit &amp; aequat. It breaketh in peeces and maketh euen or ſmooth things that be rough.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>William of He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant Earle of Oſtreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant,<note place="margin">Froſſard.</note> ſonne of Albert duke Raua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Earle of Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Holland, and Zel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> about the yeare of our Lord, 1390, carried in his frandart
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:20154:105"/>the picture of a harrow of golde, which he ſhewed in the warres and hoſt of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to the city of Barbarie called Aphrodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin. For euen as the harrow doth breake in ſunder the hard clods of the fieldes, ſo doth a good prince with the equitie of his lawes and ſtatutes reſtraine the wicked, rebellious, and ſeditious, with thoſe that oppoſe themſelues againſt his authoritie and office.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:20154:106"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lteriùs tentare veto. I forbid to attempt anie further.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Before the comming of Chriſt, the Pagans and heathen Gentiles had the truth of the myſterie of the trinitie reuealed vnto them, as it was propheſied of the God of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, whom they called <hi>Sanctum Fidium</hi> holy,<note place="margin">lond. Fla.</note> and truſtie, and <hi>Semipater</hi> halfe a father. They carried him into the citie, affirming that hee conſiſted of three names, when in deede he was but one. And although there was a temple conſecrate to that trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:20154:106"/>on Quirinal hill, yet carried it the name but of one onelie. And of ſuch great eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was that three fold image, that in al ages it had the ſoueraigntie, where vnder was figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the trinitie of the Godhead is one vnitie, to wit, <hi>Deus fidius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plinie.</note> which was the middeſt God. Thus the nation of the Sabins was moſt religious, and therefore haue they purchaſed them a name accordingly. Neither is it to be doubted, but that the olde Gentiles to whom religion was more acceptable, had greater light and knowledge of the true faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:20154:107"/>
               <head>Seruitus libera. Free ſeruice.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The rigor of Moiſes law towards ſeruants was ſuch,<note place="margin">Exod. 21. Deut. 15.</note> that he who had fulfilled the exact time of his bondage, a choiſe ſhould be giuen him, either to be ſet at libertie, or elſe to be bondman to his maiſter as long as he liued. If the ſeruant chooſe to be bonde, his maiſter ſhould bore his eare with an alle, &amp; that was called free wil ſeruice. The ſame ought euery chriſtian man to do, who, as it were a free ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant vnder the law of grace, ought to offer his eare to God, that he may make it capable, &amp; obedient to his commandements. This great
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:20154:107"/>benefit is to be imbraced of all men, which thing the Pſalmiſt ſemeth to inſinuate in this place, where he ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 39</note> thou haſt bored or made readie my eares. There are others that interprete the place of Moiſes otherwiſe, that ſuch voluntarie bondage, did ſignifie thoſe that gaue themſelues wholy to earthly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, reſeruing no time to amendement, nor yet euer ſeeking to redeeme themſelues into the libertie of the ſpirit of God (which is our ſeruice by faith in Ieſus Chriſt) wherefore their eares doe ſignifie perpetuall calamitie and miſerie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:20154:108"/>
               <head>Sic terras turbine perflat. So he troubleth the earth with whirlewindes.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>God our creator (as Saint Peter,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ames. 4. Luk. 1.</note> Iames and Luke doe witnes) doth reſiſt the proude, the high minded, louers of themſelues, and the arrogant, but giueth grace to the humble and lowlie. Wherein he ſeemeth to imitate the lightning, which leaueth vntouched thinges that are low, and ſtriking thoſe that are loftie
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:20154:108"/>and high, as Horace in theſe wordes beareth record.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>The pine apple tree is toſt with windes,</l>
                  <l>and haughtie turrets ſoone do fall,</l>
                  <l>The lightning eke doth fiercelie beate</l>
                  <l>The mountaines high and tall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Alſo Ouid.</head>
                  <l>Enuie doth often ſoare aloft,</l>
                  <l>and windes beate places hie,</l>
                  <l>And lightnings eke aſſault the place,</l>
                  <l>that mounts vp, to the skie.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:20154:109"/>
               <head>Vel in ara. And that on the holie altar.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Galeatius Marie duke of Milan, the ſonne of Francis Sforce, was of ſuch effeminate &amp; libidinous diſpoſition of minde, that he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red violence, &amp; defiled honorable matrones, and chaſt virgins. Which extreame wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes made him ſo odious both to his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; to ſtrangers which were ſubiect vnto him alſo, that in the ende it grewe to be his deſtruction. For one Andrew Lampugnan of
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:20154:109"/>Milan a courtier with the aſſiſtance of two of his companions, grieuouſly offended at him (eſpecially for the intollerable oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which the ſaid duke had vſed againſt a certaine abbot his brother, and that in the abbey or monaſterie) conſpired his death. Which conſpiracie after that Lampugnan had once conceiued in his minde, fearing to ſet vpon the prince, or to ſmite him, whoſe beautie, comelines and maieſtie, danted and appaled him, inuented a way, whereby he might both perſeuere, &amp; alſo beſtrengthened and confirmed in his purpoſe: to wit he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an image of the duke to be ingrauen verie cunning lie in a table, whereunto, as often as hee came, hee thruſt his ſword thorow it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vſed this policie a while, he was greatly confirmed to performe the deede: and ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the church with the reſt of the ſame conſpiracie, he meeteth the duke, garded with a great traine, as it were to ſalute him, and giuing him three great woundes in the bellie, he ſlue him. Thus died this miſerable and wicked prince, who conſidered not the ſaying of Claudian, that neither watching by night nor garding by day of troupes &amp; bands of men keepeth not the perſon of the prince ſo ſure as loue doth. And truly our God a iuſt
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:20154:111"/>God of reuenge hath commended to vs ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, friendſhip and peace one with another, which whoſoeuer doth breake and violate, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie where, and to the laſt breath the Lord will puniſh him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:20154:111"/>
               <head>Caelitùs impendet. The ſword of Gods wrath hanging ouer our heads.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:20154:110"/>Dionyſius the tyran being king of Sici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vpon a time perecauing himſelfe to be excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly praiſed of a certaine thraſonicall pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſite,<note place="margin">Cicero.</note> Damocles by name, for his great riche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> coſtly ornaments &amp; the like, accounting him happier then any man that liued beſides, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> anſwered the flatterer after this manner, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocles, quoth he, ſeeing that our fate doth like thee ſo well, go to, wilt thou make trial of our happines, and taſt of our fortune. Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſir, ſaid the others, if it pleaſe your grace with all my heart. Wherupon the tyran comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a chamber to be prepared for him, the poſtes and bedſteads gliſtering with gold, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cupbordes, and benches furniſhed with veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of ſiluer curiouſly wrought, and you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> men of an excellent beautie ſtanding abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the table brauely attired, as it were readie t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obey Damocles commaundement. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> were alſo oyntmentes, corolles, garlandes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> floures, and other fragrant odours. The ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble was furniſhed with all kind of dainties, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as Damocles thought himſelfe to be in the top of all felicitie, vntill at the laſt, the tyra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> commanded a naked ſworde to be hanged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a ſmall haire or thread, ouer the flatterer head, the point thereof touching his nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> where he being admoniſhed, and fearing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:20154:110"/>eminent danger, lothed that which before he thought to be the chiefeſt happines, deſpiſed the beautie of the young men, and diſdained the dainties, the golden veſſels, corols, ſweete <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dours, and elſe whatſoeuer. And being full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f feare, beſought the king to ceaſſe from ſuch dangerous ieſting, &amp; praying that ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erilous felicitie might neuer happen vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im. In which thing the tyran ſhewed ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, that there was no felicitie, where there was continuall feare, and anguiſh of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> came deſtruction. Eſpecially if we referre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his to the ſword of Gods iuſtice, hanging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er the neckes of the wicked and vngodly, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t were in a moſt ſmall and ſlender thred.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:20154:112"/>
               <head>Satis. Enough.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Heraclitus willing to inſinuate the Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens, that they ought to be content with the liberall gifts of nature, and that they ought
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:20154:112"/>to liue together in peace and tranquillitie, if they were wiſe, caſt meale with his hand into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> glaſſe full of water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Vis eſt ardentior intùs. The fire that burneth inwardly is more to be feared.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>As the fire being kindled in the middeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f a hollowe and drie ſtocke, bringeth great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ineuitable daunger by reaſon of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecret burning within: So a citie ſette on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e with ciuill diſſention, and ſedition,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:20154:113"/>thorow the ſecreat treaſons of the citizens, bringeth a fearefull danger, which cannot be eaſily remedied without great loſſe to the common welth. This allegorie may well be compared to ſecret loue, which burning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly doth bring great griefe and anguiſh to the minde, and oftentimes deſtruction it ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Premitur, non opprimitur. Preſſed, not oppreſſed.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The Emperor Galba (following in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the example of Salomon,<note place="margin">3. King. 3.</note> who tried the affection of the mothers towardes their children) when there was ſute in the lawe commenced touching the propertie of a
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:20154:113"/>certaine beaſt, with verie ſlender and weake reaſons &amp; witneſſes on either ſide, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the beaſt ſhould be carried blindfold to the place where he was wont to be watred, and vncouering his eyes,<note place="margin">Sueton.</note> to whomſoeuer he went voluntarily to be his owne for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Magnum vecligal. A great reuenue.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The Hedghegge or Vrchin ſeeking his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing verie carefully, if he find any thing, he is not content to ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is belly ful, but tumbling himſelfe vp and down<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g his prickes abroad, ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:20154:114"/>vpon the ſame, and ſo carrieth them into his dens and holes in the ground. Which beaſt teacheth vs, that it is not enough to haue large fields, and great poſſeſſions, except we vſe alſo both diligence to get, and ſparing of that which we haue got. This is a moſt ſure reuenue, and ſuch as both mightie, and rich men ought to follow, taking an example here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of from this beaſt, which vſeth ſuch care and diligence in getting of her liuing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:20154:114"/>
               <head>Ingenij largitor. Neceſſitie the miniſter of pollicie</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:20154:115"/>Neceſſity is the chiefeſt thing that ſtirreth men vp to practiſe ſubtil ie and craft: which thing the rauen (whereof Plinie ſpeaketh) hath ſufficienth procued,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> who laboring with thirſt, and ſpying a veſſell wherein was ſome water, but ſo deepe as ſhee could not drinke, ſhe filled verie craftely the veſſell with little ſtones, vntill the water which was in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, ſwelled vp to the toppe, and ſo ſhe dranke her fill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:20154:115"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>indictae trabit exitium. Reuenge draweth with it deſtruction to him that ſeeketh to reuenge.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Both thoſe that are the authors of conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies and thoſe that are acceſſaries to the ſame, do both of them deſerue puniſhment. The which thing we reade to haue happened to the 300 Foxes which Samſon ſent with fire brands tyed to them,<note place="margin">Iudges. 1</note> into the fieldes of the Philiſtines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:20154:116"/>
               <head>Aequari pauet alta minor. The lower feareth the like lot.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Tarquine the proud,<note place="margin">T. Liuius later. the great.</note> deſiring to make knowne his mind cloſely to his ſonne being
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:20154:116"/>abſent from him, and ſuppoſing it was not the beſt to reueale his intent to the noble man whom his ſonne had ſent to him, tooke him into his garden, as it were to walke, where he cut off with his ſtaffe al the higheſt heads of the Chesboles: By which act his ſonne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, it was his fathers pleaſure, that the nobles, and eſpecially the Gabionits, ouer whom togither with his father he triumphed, and thorow pollicie exerciſed no ſmal autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie amongſt them, ſhould be corrected and puniſhed with extreme puniſhment. And thus by this ſubtile deuiſe, Tarquinius ſeemed to inſinuate to his ſonne his bloudie ſentence, as though he ſuppoſed (as far as may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectured) that a prince ought to ſubdue his countrie, and make both it and all noble men elſe whatſoeuer ſubiect and obedient vnto him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:20154:117"/>
               <head>Ecquis diſcernit vtrumque? Can any man diſcerne both?</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The nature of a riddle or ſiue doth repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the good and honeſt, for euerie ſiue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:20154:117"/>the good corne, and the profitable graine, from the vnprofitable: ſo in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner both the good and the euill, haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to iudge and diſcerne betwixt the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and propertie of things, which the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked do not, but heape vp euerie thing without the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idle or fiue of reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:20154:118"/>
               <head>Hac illac perfluo. I runne out on euery ſide.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The Daniſh hogſhead as Poets do report, was ſo full of holes, &amp; ſlif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, that whatſoeuer was powred into it, ran forth againe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Plutarch,<note place="margin">Plutar. Terence</note> Tere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; other authors haue compared praters, ianglers, vngratefull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and couetous men to the ſame: for that
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:20154:118"/>clatterers or blabbers of their tongues cannot keepe any ſecrets, but vtter all, and more too: the vngratefull doth neuer thanke him that hath done him good, the couetous are neuer contented, nor ſatiſfied with enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtutis Fortuna comes. Fortune a companion of vertue.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Certaine painters deſirous to gratifie one Timotheus duke of Athens,<note place="margin">Suidas.</note> or elſe to flatter him for his great riches and power, purtayed his image in ſuch ſort, Fortune giuing him ſleeping diuerſe cities compaſſed about with tordes, and ſundrie nets of thread. Which thing Timotheus tooke in euill part, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that they rather attributed his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to Fortune,<note place="margin">Plutar.</note> then to vertue. Plutrarch writeth that it was done of thoſe that enuyed him in diſdaine, and contempt of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:20154:119"/>
               <head>Prohibere nefas. It is not lawfull to reſtraine her</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Amphisbena a moſt ſtrange ſerpent found in the deſerts of Libia, hauing a head at both ends,<note place="margin">Ariſtotle Plinie.</note> to the end that ſhe may either bite and purſue her enimie, or elſe at her pleaſure run away. Which may be a figure of double faced traitors, and ſecreat domeſticall enimies, the danger of whom is ſo much the more to be feared, by how much the more truer it is, that no peſtilence (as Cicero teſtifieth) is of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter force,<note place="margin">Cicero.</note> than this kind of men. Of whom this prouer be is wont to be vſed, in this ſenſe, In the one hand he carrieth a ſtone, in the other he ſheweth bread.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:20154:119"/>
               <head>Tu decus omne tuis. Thou art a renowne to all thy kinred.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Noble deeds, famous enterpriſes, and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious exploites brought forth the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of true and ancient nobilitie,<note place="margin">Tro. Pomp.</note> which thing the memorable example of Liſimachus the Macedonian doth proue, who is ſaid to haue left to his poſteritie a moſt notable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of the valiancie and excellencie of his minde. For being caſt amongſt the Lions
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:20154:120"/>by the comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of Alexander he think his arme into the mouth of the Lyon, &amp; pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling forth his tongue, killed him. The king ſeeing the valiancie of Liſimachus gaue him great authoritie, and cauſed a cittie which he had built to be called by his name, Liſimach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:20154:120"/>
               <head>Vſque recurrit. It runneth togither againe.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:20154:121"/>Nature which way ſoeuer it be wreſted, wil yer returne againe into his owne nature and proper condition. Experience hereof we haue in trees, into the which if thou graffeſt by art ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igges or twif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, or takeſt away the branches by violence, yet notwithſtanding they will bring forth new branches in their owne naturall height. The like is in beaſtes, and other naturall things: whereof is riſen that old adage, Thou canſt not make a good Goſhauke of a Buſtard, nor a good Courtier of a countrie clowne: for as Horace ſaith.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>The pot a long time doth retaine,</l>
                  <l>the ſmell, and eke the taſt,</l>
                  <l>Of liquor wherewithall it was,</l>
                  <l>beſmeared at the firſt.</l>
                  <l>And albeit thou doeſt deuide,</l>
                  <l>dame Fortune with a furke:</l>
                  <l>Yet ſhe againe togither runnes,</l>
                  <l>and there ſhe needs will lurke.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:20154:121"/>
               <head>Cocumque ferar. Which way ſo euer I be carried.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The ſhelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh or coc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> fiſh either of his c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, or by his forme, is alwayes readie to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imie, becauſe which way ſoeuer he
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:20154:122"/>falleth, he hath his prickes vpward; So the wicked and vngodly do continually hurt and oppreſſe with extreme miſerie thoſe with whom they haue to do.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:20154:122"/>
               <head>Spe illectat inani. The world delighteth vs with vaine hope.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The ſweete baites of worldly thinges if they be conſidered a farre off, do promiſe
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:20154:123"/>great things to men, and lift them vp into a wonderfull hope, but if they be conſidered neere hand, thou ſhalt finde that they are nothing but meere vanitie and deceipt. Such be the ſnares of batfowlers cunningly framed to intrappe the poore birds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:20154:123"/>
               <head>Vlterius ne tende obijs. Go no further for feare of Gods wrath.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The power of man, neither can, nor ought to attempt ought againſt the power of God, as it was reuealed to Valentinus the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,<note place="margin">Gregory Nazianz.</note> who being infected with the hereſie of
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:20154:124"/>the Arrians, after that he had writ with his owne hand many things concerning the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, and baniſhment of Baſill, he was not able to make an end, his penne refuſing three times to let downe any more inke. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he reſtrained not himſelfe from confirming and ratifying his wicked law, and decree, before a great trembling inuaded his hand, wherewith he being ſtrooken, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing great feare withall, what ſo euer he had writ, he rent it preſently.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:20154:124"/>
               <head>Haec conſcia numinis aetas. This age knoweth God aright.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>About the raigne of Auguſtus Caeſar (as Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie beareth record) there appeared at Rome a ſtarre garland,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> or crowne round about the ſunne, as it had beene of wheate eares, with circles of ſundrie colours.<note place="margin">Sueton.</note> Suetonius ſpeaking of this wonder, remembreth but of one cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, like the rainebowe, compaſſing in the globe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. But Dion following narrowly the deſcription of Plinie,<note place="margin">Dion.</note> beſides that ſtrange
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:20154:125"/>ſtarre which then appeared, and that vnaccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed, affirmeth alſo that the light of the ſunne was darkened by reaſon of three other greater circles compaſſing it about, one wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of repreſented the forme of a garla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of eares. Dion addeth farther that the ſun gaue ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what a dimme light, now &amp; then in the night. But this is certaine, that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt the true light, and true ſonne of righteouſnes was borne in the dayes of Auguſtus Caeſar, whoſe birth and comming into the world, bringing a heape of al goodnes to man, might as wel be reuealed by the miniſterie of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, as his paſſion and death was foreſhewed according to the Goſpel, to wit, when the ſon was obſcured, and darkneſſe was throughout al the world. But it ought not to ſeeme ſtrange although the ſignes and wonders that went before Chriſts birth, were obſerued of the heathen, albeit otherwiſe ignorant, when as thoſe things which followed his paſſion and reſurrection were had in great eſtimation, to wit, the darkeneſſe being noted by Dioniſius Areopagita, whileſt that wandring thorow Egypt with Apollophanes his ſchoolemaſter, he ſtudied Philoſophie, &amp; through the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his wit and knowledge,<note place="margin">Suidas.</note> perceiuing the ſun to be darkned beyond the courſe of
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:20154:125"/>nature: ſaid, either the God of nature doth ſuffer, or the engine of the world is diſſolued.<note place="margin">Plinie in his. 2. booke.</note> Moreouer concerning the earthquake before the reſurrection of Chriſt in Plinie after the iuſt computation of yeares, we find theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes written and recorded.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>An earthquake huge in Caeſars dayes,</l>
                  <l>Tiberius did befall,</l>
                  <l>Where thorow twelue cities of Aſia,</l>
                  <l>were quite ſubuerted all.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="202" facs="tcp:20154:126"/>
               <head>Haud ſidit inane. An egge being emptie ſwimmeth aloft.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>An egge that is new and full of iuyce being caſt into the deepe,<note place="margin">Plinie. Quintil.</note> ſincketh downe preſently, but a rotten one being caſt into the water ſwimmeth a loft. So by how much the leſſe wiſedome is in a man, by ſo much the more doth he bewray his folly by his ſelfe loue, and ambition. Vpon the other ſide, how much
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:20154:126"/>the wiſer a man is, ſo much the humbler, and quieter of minde he is, and far from all brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and oſtentation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Infringit ſolido. He breaketh the rocke.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>He that ſtudieth to reproch or to ſlander the godlineſſe, or conſtancie of a wiſe man, the euil it ſelfe ſhal light vpon his owne head, euen as an arrow ſhot againſt a hard ſtone or rocke reſulteth back againe, and hurteth him that caſt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="204" facs="tcp:20154:127"/>
               <head>Sans autre guide. Without any guide.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Brome ſtalkes or other boughes tyed to ſtiles, or ſtucke vp by heapes of ſtones erected by trauellers to direct them in their way, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth that vertue is the onely guide to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting felicitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="205" facs="tcp:20154:127"/>
               <head>Fata obstant. Deſtenies do withſtand.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="206" facs="tcp:20154:128"/>The getting of riches, and deſired happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is a thing verie hard, and vneaſie to be come by. Adde hereto, that pouertie doth greatly hinder the ſame good proceeding, and remoueth the acceſſe to the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Terit &amp; teritur. It weares and is worne.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>As a ſtone ſharping of iron, by continuall rubbing of the ſame iron is conſumed, ſo the
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:20154:128"/>wicked, and he that followeth contention, vexeth and tormenteth himſelfe, ſo that he may bring others to deſtruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Sic praedae patet eſca ſui. So her meat lyeth open to her own deſtruction.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The great commoditie which the fiſh cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Purple receiueth by his tongue, is ſo much the more to be eſteemed, becauſe thereby ſhee getteth her liuing. But for that ſometimes euill happeneth to her there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, there is ſhe ſo much the more to feare, becauſe by the ſame ſhe may incurre the danger of death, and become a pray to the fiſhers. Euen ſo ſtandeth the office or dutie
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:20154:129"/>of mans tongue whileſt it is wiſely gouerned, it is a moſt precious iewell, contrarily, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing giuen to backbiting, cogging &amp; lying, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theth forth fearefull and deadly poyſon: whereof it groweth that the common ſort cal ſuch a tongue <hi>grandem linguam,</hi> a brode or large tongue, or a blabbe tongue. Verie wel therefore is it compared to the tongue of a great purple fiſh, becauſe there cleaueth to the palite of her mouth a purple, red humor, ſignifying allegorically the cruel poiſon of an euill ſpeaker, a backbiter, and a bloodie fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="209" facs="tcp:20154:129"/>
               <head>Candor illaeſus. Brightnes that cannot be annoied.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Clemens de Medicis, the ſeuenth of that name Biſhop of Rome, vſed for his Enſigne a blaſing ſtarre or comet. Ariſtotle for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining thereof ſaith:<note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note> Euen as euerie newe
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:20154:130"/>comet hath neuer heeretofore portended to men either proſperous ſucceſſe and good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, or elſe ſome great hurt and detriment: ſo by the gouernment of a newe prince in a common weale, either abundance of felicitie or finall deſtruction followeth therevpon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="211" facs="tcp:20154:130"/>
               <head>Proſper vterque mari. Both appearing together vpon the ſea, is a a ſigne of good lucke.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="212" facs="tcp:20154:131"/>When two fires which our elders called by the name of Caſtor and Pollux doe appeare together, they foreſhew a proſperous voyage and good luck, but if one alone doth appeare, it is a ſigne and token of euill lucke to inſue: In like manner if the loue betwixte the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and the wife doeth flouriſh in a houſe, it is a certaine ſigne of tranquilitie and dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall happines. But vppon the other ſide, if thorough the frowardnes of either of them they be diuided, it fore ſheweth ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to be at hand. Furthermore, vnder the ſolitude or onelie appearnace of one of them, may bee vnderſtoode howe petillous a thing it is, to haue riches and authority with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wiſdome to gouerne well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="213" facs="tcp:20154:131"/>
               <head>Sic ſpectanda fides. So is faith to be tried.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The goodnes of gold is not onely try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ringing, but alſo by the touchſtone: ſo the triall of godlines and faith is to bee made not of wordes onely, but alſo by the action &amp; performance of the deedes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="214" facs="tcp:20154:132"/>
               <head>Sic violenta. So violent.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Iangling and prating out of time, and to ſmall purpoſe, is very wel compared to the blas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ering noiſe of a whisking winde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="215" facs="tcp:20154:132"/>
               <head>Terror &amp; error. Feare and terror.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>It is to bee counted one of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt pointes of a valiant Captaine, if he know to alter and chaunge daunger into ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. As for example, If hee bee inferiour vnto his enemie in regarde of time and place, to conueigh awaie both himſelfe and
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:20154:133"/>his arme from their violence and force by ſome kinde of deuice or pollicie, and making himſelfe ſeeme terrible to his foes, as Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l that noble Captaine did once, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to feare his enemies withall, he tied firebrandes to the heads of his oxen in the night ſeaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="217" facs="tcp:20154:133"/>
               <head>Poco àpoco. By little and little.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The graſſe groweth and increaſeth vppon the ground, and yet no man can perceiue his increaſe: ſo honeſtie and vertue cannot eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie be perceiued but by example &amp; practiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="218" facs="tcp:20154:134"/>
               <head>Aemula naturae. And enuious imitator of nature.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Diligence and continuall exerciſe doubtleſſe is of ſuch great force, that at the length it imitateth and matcheth nature her
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:20154:134"/>her ſelfe, which thing is verified in Domitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus the Emperour, who had ſuch ſingular skil and dexteritie in throwing the dart, that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting two at a wilde beaſt, hit him vppon the forehead ſo cunningly, that the beaſt ſeemed to ſtande as though he had had two naturall hornes growing vpon his head.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="220" facs="tcp:20154:135"/>
               <head>Renouata iuuentus. Youth is to be renued.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="221" facs="tcp:20154:135"/>The Gouſhauke is wont to prune her ſelfe, &amp; ſet her fethers in order againſt the beames of the Sunne: ſo hee that will come to Chriſt our Lord, it behoueth him to put off all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes and ſinne, and tobe clothed with new apparell, and amendement of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="222" facs="tcp:20154:136"/>
               <head>Praepete penna. With a ſpeedie wing.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="223" facs="tcp:20154:136"/>The picture of the ſpread Eagle, after the common opinion, began to be carried in inſignes and ſtandardes after this manner. There happened diviſion in the Empire, and therefore was it tranſlated in Charles the great his daies, into the Eaſt and W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt parts, (as Wolfangus Lazius hiſtoriographer to the king of the Romanes ſaith) in the dayes of Conſtantine the great, who of the common weale of Rome being one, made two, the one the Romane Empire, the other the Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinopolitane Empire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="224" facs="tcp:20154:137"/>
               <head>Attendite vobis. Take heed to your ſelues.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="225" facs="tcp:20154:137"/>To eſtabliſh the ſtate of chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,<note place="margin">Act. 20.</note> and to preſerue the ſoundnes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie of the ſame, it ſhall be neceſſarie that the faithfull preachers of Gods word by their examples and liuing doe exerciſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir dutie of preaching the worde diligently without ceaſing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="226" facs="tcp:20154:138"/>
               <head>Viuit ad extremum. The notch burneth to the laſt peece thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Euerie ones loue and faithfulnes towards his prince ought to be moſt conſtant &amp; firme,
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:20154:138"/>and ſuch as may not bee ſhaken ot extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed through anie force of winds or tempeſts ruſhing in, to wit, becauſe we ſeeme to keepe our watch rounde, that the more the windes blowe, the ſurer it keepeth fire burning ſtill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="228" facs="tcp:20154:139"/>
               <head>Captiue libertè. A captiue or ſeruile libertie.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="229" facs="tcp:20154:139"/>The conſpirators of the death of Iulius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar diſſoluing the Senate,<note place="margin">Appian.</note> carried through the ſtreetes in Rome a hat or cap vpon the point of a ſpeare, (which was a token of libertie and freedome) becauſe then it was a cuſtome to giue to Saints a cap or a hat, &amp; to make them free: by this deuice ſtirring vp the people of Rome againſt the ciuill magiſtrates, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them vndoubted libertie. But it fell out farre otherwiſe, for the ſame yeare all they were put to the ſword that were of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie. Hereby it appeareth, that that licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious libertie to ſinne, which ſome ſuppoſe to be libertie, is mere ſeruitude and bondage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="230" facs="tcp:20154:140"/>
               <head>Police ſouueraine. A perfect common wealth.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="231" facs="tcp:20154:140"/>To a perfect common wealth theſe two things be required, the pen and the ſwoorde, that is, councell and good letters in delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of affaires, and the ſworde in the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Superſtitio religioni proxima. Superſtition is next to religion.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>This is the ſtudie &amp; practiſe of our ancient enemie the deuil, that as often as hee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to ſpred abroad any peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t errors or impiety into the world, ſuch is his craft &amp; peruerſitie,
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:20154:141"/>hee couereth it vnder the ſhadowe or name of truth, albeit his intent be nothing elſe but meere deceit, a counterfet iangling, and as it were, a bewitching of men. Which thing he notablie brought to paſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it. Liuius.</note> when hee brought in the horrible ſuperſtition of diuination and ſouth ſaying, perſwading Priſcus Tarquinius the king, and the Romanes that Decius Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius the augurer diuided into two partes a great rocke with a little knife.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="233" facs="tcp:20154:141"/>
               <head>Demal mepaiſts. I am nouriſhed in him that is euill.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The boxing glaſſe that Phiſitions vſe, which are ſaid to be windie, do ſuck vp and exhauſt the corrupt bloud:<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> but the minde that is wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly inclined, ſeeketh after nothing but that which is euill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="234" facs="tcp:20154:142"/>
               <head>Fons inuocantis. The fountaine of inuocation.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Sampſon ſometimes troubled or verie hard beſtead with a meruailous great thirſt, called for helpe at Gods hands, who preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiued comfort or eaſe of water that iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued out of the iawe bone of an aſſe,<note place="margin">Iudg. 15.</note> wherwith not long before he had ſlain a thouſand men. By which miracle wee are to learne that anie thing whatſoeuer, be it neuer ſo ſimple, is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God, ſo that it be implored and deſired by his diuine worde, which is the true and liuely fountaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="235" facs="tcp:20154:142"/>
               <head>Et l'vn, et l'autre. As well the one as the other.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>When two men are fighting or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending together in what contention or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe ſo euer, it cannot be with what excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie or ſtrength or equitie either of them ſtriue, but that one ſide or other catcheth ſome vexation or trouble, if not harme: and ſo it fareth in euerie point with thoſe that
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:20154:143"/>contend in the place of exerciſe, and in the handling of the ſtaffe, wherein they contend for ſtrength, where, no not the ouercommet himſelfe carrieth awaie the victorie without greate forcing and ſtrayning of his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="237" facs="tcp:20154:143"/>
               <head>Conſultori peſſimum. Iuill councell is worſt to the councell giuer.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="238" facs="tcp:20154:144"/>It is moſt certaine that the puniſhment which another deſerueth by committing of offence, doth alwaies returne vpon the head of the firſt counceller. Wee may daille ſee this in ſtandards &amp; Enſignes of warre, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we muſter or gather ſouldiers together to their voiage, and in battell, arme our ſelues by them, as our guides againſt the enemie: for they abide the firſt onſet and renting in peeces. Nay rather the authors of battels and ſtrife in al diſſenſions and variances, are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier of the ſorer puniſhment, and the lawes themſelues command, that ſeuerer puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be inflicted vppon them, than vpon the fighters themſelues. And to the preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe belongeth that which Aulus. Gellius writeth of the wicked dealing of the Hetru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian ſouthſaiers.<note place="margin">Au. Gel.</note> For they beeing called vpon by the Romanes, that they ſhould in open aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie conſulte about Horatius Cocles i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, that was ſtriken with lightning (as they were priuie enemies of the Romanes) after that they had decreed that the image ſhould be carried into a more deſert place, where the Sunne could not come to it at al to bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit it. When accuſation of this their deuice was made, and their falſhood and trecherie in this caſe made knowen, they were killed, &amp;
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:20154:144"/>the image it ſelfe was tranſlated with a great deale more honor into Vulcans court or hall. Wherfore the young youth turning this falſe diuination into a more plauſible interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the common wealth (becauſe, as good lucke woulde haue it, it fell out happilie for the common wealth) went crying vp &amp; down the Citie, and in great choler as it were<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> broke forth into theſe ſpeeches: Euill councell is worſt to the councell giuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="240" facs="tcp:20154:145"/>
               <head>Vis neſcia vinci. Force that cannot bee ouercome with force.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="241" facs="tcp:20154:145"/>Plutarch writeth that Scylurus of Chaero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea lying vpon his deathbed,<note place="margin">Plutar.</note> offred to his 80. ſonnes one by one a bundle of dartes or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, to be broken in peeces. The which when they went about to do, and could not preuaile, and had anſwered that it was vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, their father vntied the bundle, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them euerie one out one after another, broke them with great facilitie and eaſe, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them thereby, that they were inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; vnable to be ouercome, as long as they continued in peaceable league, and quietnes togither, but if they were once drawne one from another by diſſention, and ſedition, they would eaſily fall into captiuitie, and into their enimies hands. That which Plinie noteth not much vnilke to this, might hither be adduced,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> of the ſtones of Scyrus lying in one of the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clades, which being whole, ſwome vpon the toppe of the water, but being broken, they ſuncke by and by. Therefore let this ſimbole of darts faſt ioyned togither in a bundle, and alſo of the forenamed ſtones ſignifie thus much, that leagues of what couenants ſoeuer are inuincible, if you vſe prudence for the band of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="242" facs="tcp:20154:146"/>
               <head>Quis contra nos? If God be with vs, who can be againſt vs.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Saint Paul when he was in the Iland of Malta a Viper light vpon his hand,<note place="margin">Acts. 28.</note> yet recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:20154:146"/>he no hurt thereby (although the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians thought otherwiſe) but ſhooke off the Viper into the middeſt of the fire, whereof we may ſee, that they to whom Gods mercie is readie at hand, nothing can hurt, or annoy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Maturè. Speedily.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Looke for what reaſon Titus Veſpaſian the Emperor in times paſt, vſed an Anker with a Dolphin fiſh for his cognizance or armes, for the ſame (as I thinke) Pope Paul the third vſed a Camelion with a Dolphin. Meaning thereby that the like ſlow celerity, or haſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king is alwayes to be kept in any manner of thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="244" facs="tcp:20154:147"/>
               <head>Lex publica Principis ignes. A publike law is the fire of the Prince.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="245" facs="tcp:20154:147"/>The burning firebrands which the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines were wont to carrie before their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (as we may ſee in moſt of the monuments and coynes of ancient kings, whereof Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian maketh mention,<note place="margin">Herodian</note> where he writeth of the diuination of Gordianus Caeſar) do plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignifie, that Princes, Emperors, captaines, and pretors (vnto whom authoritie vnder the king was committed to determine cauſes) ought to ſhine before all others in the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of vertue, and equitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="246" facs="tcp:20154:148"/>
               <head>In ſe contexta recurrit. Being platted togither it cleaueth faſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The Pſalmiſt making mention of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurable bountifulneſſe and liberalitie of
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:20154:148"/>Gods grace, pietie, clemencie, and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſaith, <hi>Benedices coronae anni benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis tuae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 64.</note> thou crowneſt the yeare with thy goodneſſe, and thy ſteppes droppe fatnes. Whereby he giueth vs to vnderſtand, that a yearely renuing, and a ſucceſſiue and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall returning of plentiouſneſſe of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, and yearely profites, is giuen vs from the Lord in all abundance, where alſo by the figure of a ſerpent the yeare is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood according to the monuments of the Egyptians, which they vſed in ſteed of letters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="248" facs="tcp:20154:149"/>
               <head>Pythone peremto. The ſerpent being ſlaine.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The power of the Romaine empire began then to decay, when the honor that the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:20154:149"/>were wont to haue by the authoritie of ancient lawes, decreaſed by little and little, in ſo much that the Egle in their martiall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes yeelded to the Woolfe, to the mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taure, to the horſe, and to the wild bore. The Dragon had the laſt place, whom Claudianus famouſly ſetteth forth in many of his verſes,<note place="margin">Claud.</note> the ſimilitude whereof ſignifieth continuall watchfulneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="250" facs="tcp:20154:150"/>
               <head>Caelo imperium iouis extulit ales. The Egle hath lifted vp the gouernment of the Empire to the heauens.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="251" facs="tcp:20154:150"/>The Egle hath alwayes bene the chiefeſt enſigne amongſt the Romaines, the which euen at this day belongeth to the holy Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. And this Caius Marius, after that he had attained to the honour of the ſecond Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, dedicating an Egle altogither to his legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or armies, according to Plinie his relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, preferred before all other enſignes.<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> And the Egle, becauſe ſhe is formidable and to be feared before all other birds, and as though (as it is commonly ſaid) ſhe is counted for the king of all birds, was choſen for a ſimbole or enſigne, to ſignifie a people, or nation which hath ſubdued all other whatſoeuer. But this alſo is true, that in the Romanes enſignes the Egle was wont to carrie the ſimilitude of lightning, either as a bird dedicated to Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or as carrying his armes and enſignes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, or finally becauſe, as Plinie ſaith, ſhe is neuer touched with lightning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="252" facs="tcp:20154:151"/>
               <head>Infestis tutamen aquis. A defence or ſafegard in the dangerous waters.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Seruius Galba the Emperor ſignified by this ſimbole,<note place="margin">Dion.</note> as wel his own act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, as his anceſtor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Therfore he purtrayed a dogge bowing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe downe from the forepart of the ſhip, like as though he would leape downe: wherby he declared great vigilancie, and conſtant wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching againſt all dangers whatſoeuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="253" facs="tcp:20154:151"/>
               <head>Antidoti ſalubris amaror. Holſome is the Antidotes bitterneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="254" facs="tcp:20154:152"/>The ſumme of our ſaluation conſiſteth chiefely in the imitation of the miſerie of the paſſion, and croſſe of our redeemer Ieſus Chriſt; namely, as we ſaid before, if we pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently beare the afflictions of this tranſitorie world, that ſo we calling vpon the name of Chriſt, may vſe our ſelues thereto, and may change the bitternes of the croſſe into the cuppe of ſaluation, ſinging with the pſalmiſt, What ſhall I render to the Lord for all the good things which he hath giuen vnto me?<note place="margin">Pſal. 116</note> I will take the cuppe of ſaluation, and will call vpon the name of the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="255" facs="tcp:20154:152"/>
               <head>Ceſſit victoria victis. Victorie is happened to the ouercome.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="256" facs="tcp:20154:153"/>By this meanes the bloody effuſion of blood is turned in the holy Martyrs and thoſe that ſuffer for the name of God, into the forme of a crowned Palme tree, or elſe an euerlaſting reward of a victorie gotten, that ſo the crowne of an immortall kingdome might be ſignified. But not thoſe onely which ſhed their blood for the confeſſion of their faith, are therefore thought worthie of the name of Martyrs, but they which following the Lord Chriſt, for the inheritance of the kingdome of heauen, take vp his croſſe, paciently bearing the contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and reproches of this world, wherein the chiefeſt kinde of martyrdome is for the moſt part occupied, and exerciſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="257" facs="tcp:20154:153"/>
               <head>Flaueſcent. In time they will become yellow or ripe.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Horatius Farneſius duke of Cameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, vſed the like quaternion of greene ſheaues of wheate, whereby he declared or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured, that the young youth of the noble prince (as I ſuppoſe) ſhould in time be turned into a ripe and full age.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="258" facs="tcp:20154:154"/>
               <head>Vt lapſu grauiore ruant. That they may fall with the greater ruine.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>There is perpetuall enimitie betwixt the dragon &amp; the Egle.<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> Whereby it commeth to paſſe that they neuer meete one the other, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a fierce conflict, &amp; ſo dangerouſly are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried togither thorow the aire, that the Egle wrapped round about in the dragons taile,
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:20154:154"/>they fall headlong downe togither. The like is wont to happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to proud &amp; hauty perſons whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are at contention amongſt themſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictrix casta fides. Pure faith is a conqueror.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>In the church of the Franciſcanes, the bewtiful enſignes of the famous citty A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:20154:155"/>are ingrauen, on the tombe of the noble woman Laure, which is ſo much comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of Franciſcus Petrarcha, with two little laurel bowes lying a croſſe one ouer another, with the forme of a croſſe alſo added to it, ſtanding ouerthwart in the middle, &amp; vpon them the ſhape of a Roſe faſtened to the middle of the Target. Whereby is ſignified the integritie of their firſt faith and promiſe ioyned with chaſtitie, and the ſubdued affections of this wicked world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="261" facs="tcp:20154:155"/>
               <head>Ipſa ſuae testis victoria cladis. Victorie it ſelfe is a witneſſe of his owne deſtruction.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>There is found euen at this day ancient coynes, with the inſcription of Veſpaſianus Caeſar vpon them, wherein there is ingrauen
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:20154:156"/>the figure of a high Palme tree abounding with great ſtore of fruite. Furthermore it is moſt certaine that that moſt noble and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tree grew in Iudea, when it was ſubdued, and brought into ſubiection by the force and power of that mightie Prince. Wherfore this preſaging type of the Palme tree, doth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie not onely the region of Iurie, but alſo the deſtruction of that nation, and Gods perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall deſtruction againſt the poſteritie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="263" facs="tcp:20154:156"/>
               <head>Mala vndique clades. Deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> waiteth for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked in euery place</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe ſwords which are placed &amp; ſtand forth of a round circle, and a trembling Hare in the middeſt thereof, do ſignifie vnto vs, that a ſafe refuge, is in no place granted to offenders, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the field, or in the citty, or in any other place in bodie or ſpirite. For ſo both in infinite other places, and alſo in Moſes the ſcripture threatneth, ſaying,<note place="margin">Deut. 31</note> The ſword ſhall deſtroy them abrode, and feare at home.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="264" facs="tcp:20154:157"/>
               <head>Grandeur, per grand heur. Authoritie and dignitie commeth of Fortune.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Dion reporteth that three monuments of triumph,<note place="margin">Dion.</note> were ingrauen in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peyus, wherewithall he vſed to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le, like as Scylla vſed to haue. The which ſimbole without all doubt, foreſheweth a monument of the noble exploits of them both.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="265" facs="tcp:20154:157"/>
               <head>Improbitas ſubigit rectum. Wickedneſſe oppreſſeth the good.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="266" facs="tcp:20154:158"/>As a tree is kept from growing, and choked as it were by the growing of Iuie about the ſame, ſo a matter in law, although it be neuer ſo vniuſt, thorow the art and wit of the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent lawier doth wreſt the law after their owne will and pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="267" facs="tcp:20154:158"/>
               <head>Pacis &amp; armorum vigiles. The watchers of peace and warre.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>By the watching clocke of the cocke and the trumpet, it is eaſie to iudge what diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there is betwixt the condition of warre and peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="268" facs="tcp:20154:159"/>
               <head>De paruis grandis aceruus erit. Great heapes come of ſmall beginnings.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>From an eare to a handful, from a handful to a ſheaue. So a poore man by good councell, wiſedome &amp; diligence ought to vſe the good gifts that are lawful for him, &amp; giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him.
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:20154:159"/>Wherto when he is come by Gods benefites, it is needfull that he ſtay himſelfe ſometimes, &amp; ſix that moſt f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtunate ſufficiency of things being a true crowne of riches for a marke or ſcope: remembring in this caſe alwayes theſe verſes of a certaine french Poet (whoſe name if I knew, I would no more conceale it, then I would his worthie praiſe which he deſerueth by it) as followeth.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of nothing, or then nothing leſſe,</l>
                  <l>if poſſiblie there could be,</l>
                  <l>To little many oft do come,</l>
                  <l>by Gods permiſſion free.</l>
                  <l>And force ſo great this little hath,</l>
                  <l>that it each one permits,</l>
                  <l>That to that which ſufficeth well,</l>
                  <l>he often largely hits.</l>
                  <l>If ſo that this ſufficiencie,</l>
                  <l>of goods him well content,</l>
                  <l>But if perhaps to attaine to much,</l>
                  <l>he couetouſly be bent,</l>
                  <l>Being not content with that which might</l>
                  <l>full well him ſatiſfie,</l>
                  <l>Moſt certaine perils bide that mind,</l>
                  <l>which to and fro doth ſlie.</l>
                  <l>Leſt iuſtly he returne againe,</l>
                  <l>(beleeue contented tis)</l>
                  <l>To former ſtate (as heretofore)</l>
                  <l>full bare and poore iwis.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="270" facs="tcp:20154:160"/>
               <head>Là, le danger. In warres is all miſchiefe and danger.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="271" facs="tcp:20154:160"/>There ſtood in Lacedemon the picture of Bacchus, holding a long ſpeare with Iuie round about it, growing vp to the verie point thereof, which was couered with the ſame. Which ſignified that wars were to be waged, not by force, or might, but were to be directed by councell, pollicie, and art: for to ſuch arts martiall force is ſubiect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="272" facs="tcp:20154:161"/>
               <head>Nodos Virtute reſoluo. I reſolue all doubts onely by vertue.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="273" facs="tcp:20154:161"/>By this Symbole of the Marſhal of S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew, being an arme and a ſwoord, which is ſayde properly to belong to Alexander the great, cutting in ſunder Gordius knot in the ancient pallas of Midas, may be vnderſtoode (in my opinion) the prowes of the valyant Prince. And alſo, that things beeing other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe vneaſie and difficult, are by manhod and ſtrength made eaſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="274" facs="tcp:20154:162"/>
               <head>Turpibus exitium. Deſtruction hangeth ouer the heads of the wicked and vncleane.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>As the Bittle is bred and nouriſhed in the excrements and dong of a horſe, but beeing in the middeſt of roſes dieth: ſo theſe youths
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:20154:162"/>that are ſo nice, &amp; giuen ouer to carnall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the ſtudie of godlineſſe and other good vertues delighteth them not, deſiring rather to be polluted with the filthie dong of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall pleaſure and wickednes.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="278" facs="tcp:20154:163"/>
               <p>in a martiall Enſigne, is a perpetuall monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the protection of the kingdome of France.<note place="margin">Eng. de Monſt.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Etiam fortunam. Yea, fortune too.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>M. Sergius a Romane knight, after that hee had many times fought with Hannibal,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> and being taken captiue by ſubtitltie, had eſcaped his hands, at laſt in a skirmiſh loſt his right
<pb n="279" facs="tcp:20154:163"/>hand: whereupon hee was conſtrained to fight with his lefte hande in foure other bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels. But when hee perceiued that hee coulde not vſe the one hand ſo aptly as the other, he cauſed an yron hand to bee made, and ſet faſt to his right arme. The which he ſo luckilie &amp; valiantly vſed after in field, that he ouercame &amp; diſcomfited twelue armies in France, that were ſworne enemies to the Romanes. For which cauſe Plinie writeth that hee knoweth not anie other that is to bee preferred before Sergius in prowes and manhoode, who van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing the violence of his fortune, made himſelfe worthie of all the praiſe and honor of thoſe victories.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="280" facs="tcp:20154:164"/>
               <head>Sic ſopor irrepat. So ſleepe came vpon him.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Wee reade it written in the French Chronicles, that one Gontranus king of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundie, being vppon a time wearie with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,<note place="margin">Annals of France.</note> and falling on ſleepe, his ſeruants wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching by him in a certain field, by a riuer ſide running hard by, there came out of the kings mouth a little beaſt, and aſſaied to paſſe ouer the riuer. VVhich when the kinges ſeruant ſawe, he drew out his ſword, whervpon as on a bridge, the little beaſt paſſed ouer the riuer, &amp;
<pb n="281" facs="tcp:20154:164"/>went into a hole or caue that was in a hill o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer againſt it. From whence ſhe came foorth againe by and by, and going ouer againe by the ſword as by a bridge, went againe into the kings mouth. VVhen the king awaked, he told his man the like dreime that he had ſeene, to wit, that he went ouer a riuer vpon an yron bridge, and ſo into a caue vnder a hill, where he ſawe great treaſure hidde. When his man heard that, he tolde him in order what had happened when he was on ſleepe. So the king cauſed the inner parte of the hill to bee ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whereout he digged abundance of golde and ſiluer, which he beſtowed vpon the poore and needie, and alſo gaue much to the vſe of diuerſe Churches. And alſo with the ſame treaſure he cauſed the coffine of Saint Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell neere to Chalon at Saona, where he was thought to be buried.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="282" facs="tcp:20154:165"/>
               <head>Caecus amor prolis. Loue of parents to their children is blind or voide of reaſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The Ape is ſayde to loue his young ones ſo vnmeaſurablie,<note place="margin">Plinie.</note> that whileſt hee clippeth them in his armes more then reaſon would,
<pb n="283" facs="tcp:20154:165"/>hee after killeth them with griping them ſo faſt to him. In like manner many parents are wont to be ſo lauiſh in the nice education of their children, that with their too much coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering of them, at the laſt they bring them to naught.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="284" facs="tcp:20154:166"/>
               <head>Supplicio laus tuta ſemel. Hee that was worthie of praiſe was one free from puniſhment.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>It is recorded of a certaine Indian, that was of ſuch dexteritie in throwing of a
<pb n="285" facs="tcp:20154:166"/>dart, that he could caſt it a great way off tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugh a ring of ſmall compaſſe. VVherefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen he was commanded by king Alexander to ſhew his cunning before him, hee coulde not by anie meanes bee perſwaded to doe it. For the which cauſe hee was condemned by the kings ſentence to die. And beeing asked therefore he would not do ſo ſmall a matter for the kings pleaſure, anſwered, that hee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed leaſt hee ſhould happilie miſſe of his vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all cuſtome of throwing. When Alexander ſawe that he did it, not ſo much for rebellion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s for feare and ſhame, hee commanded the condemned man to be ſet at libertie, wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at his diſpoſition, which was verie deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of glorie, deſiring rather to die than to diminiſh or diſcredit the fame and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti: of his knowledge and cunning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="286" facs="tcp:20154:167"/>
               <head>Omnis caro foenum. All fleſh is graſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>If this people which before all other nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vainely vexed and troubled the whole
<pb n="287" facs="tcp:20154:167"/>world, that they might ſtill increaſe and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance their owne power and glorie, &amp; make immortall as it were, had at the laſt vſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome good and wholeſome councell, and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed into their own ſtate, that they might ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and deeply at the length haue weighed that the ſymbole, and author, and father as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere,<note place="margin">Ouid. Seruius</note> Romulus (which was a bundell of haie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anged vpon a pik or lance) meant, they had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euer ſuſtained ſo many, and ſo great vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both of bodie and minde, eſpecially behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo ſodaine an alteration of humane af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and moſt of all, of thoſe things which belong properly to this fleſhly and earthlie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ody, whoſe mutabilitie and inconſtancie the Prophet compareth to greene graſſe and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing floures.<note place="margin">Eſay. 40</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="288" facs="tcp:20154:168"/>
               <head>Tolle vpluptatum ſtimulos. Take awaie the prickes of pleaſures.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>As we are wont to vſe a flap made of the ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or ſtarred feathers of a pecocke to beate awaie I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s:<note place="margin">S. Ierome</note> ſo wee ought to driue from vs &amp; to purge our ſelues of pleaſure, and all kinde of fleſhly luſt with great watchfulnes &amp;c re.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="289" facs="tcp:20154:168"/>
               <head>Paix outragée ſe rend vengée. Fooliſh peace is wont alwaies to render vengeance.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="290" facs="tcp:20154:169"/>The Perſians in the daies of Zeno the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſuffered due puniſhment for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, for the hoſt of the Perſians had thought by ſubtiltie to ruſhe headlong vpon Caeſars Enſignes (where vppon conditions of peace concluded of betwixte both the nations,<note place="margin">Procop.</note> did hang and was ſhewed) and to rende them in peeces. But ere they were aware, the Perſian king with his children and the chiefe of his armie were taken in a trench which the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes had prepared. And alſo not long after all the reſt of the armie that were left by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie were diſcomfited, and not one left which was not deſtroied.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="291" facs="tcp:20154:169"/>
               <head>Rerum Sapientia cuſtos. Wiſdome the preſeruer of all things.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="292" facs="tcp:20154:170"/>The moſt gracious Dutches of Berie, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet by name, expreſſed the ſingular affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her hart in this Embleme of two ſerpents, putting foorth both their heades out of the boughes of an Oliue tree: ſhewing that the true gouernment of all things is beſt helde faſt, and holden vp by the maſt of wiſedome and pollicie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="293" facs="tcp:20154:170"/>
               <head>Diſcite iuſtitiam moniti. Learne iuſtice by admonition.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="294" facs="tcp:20154:171"/>Whither ſo euer Baſanus king of the Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cambrians Diocles ſonne went, he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alwaies a ſword to be carried before him, on the top wherof was faſtned a rope or hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that for a teſtimonie of inuiolate iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. For he was a king, beſides that hee was famous in all other vertues, that was alſo a diligent cenſor and keeper of iudgement and equitie, inſomuch that hee ſpared not in his owne ſonne when hee offended, but ſeuerelie puniſhed him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="295" facs="tcp:20154:171"/>
               <head>Concuſſus ſurgo. Being ſmaller, I mount aloft.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The Admirall Cabotius alwaies vſed for his armes, a round circle or globe like a ball, (that I may ſo tearme it) ſwelling with wind, with this inſcription, I ſhaken and toſt, doe ariſe, which ſufficiently vnfoldeth this ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="296" facs="tcp:20154:172"/>
               <head>Hâc virtutis iter. This is the waie to vertue.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>A fielde rake or harrow tied to the letter y (which they call one of the Pythagoricall characters) which Marcus Petrus Moruillier chanceller of France, challenged to himſelfe
<pb n="297" facs="tcp:20154:172"/>for his armes, as wee may ſee in the Church dedicate to S. Martin in the fieldes in the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Paris, doeth giue vs ſufficient admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that labour doeth make the waie to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine vnto vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="398" facs="tcp:20154:173"/>
               <head>Hoc Caeſar me donauit. Caeſar hath rewarded me with this chaine.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Charles the ſixt king of the Francons hunting in the foreſt of Senliana for a Hart that had about his necke a chaine or wreath
<pb n="299" facs="tcp:20154:173"/>of braſſe burniſhed with gold, with an inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this effect: This Caeſar hath me giuen, and deſiring to leaue behind him this memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable pray to the knowledge of his poſteritie, tooke a running Hart for his armes, hauing his necke compaſſed about with a crowne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="300" facs="tcp:20154:174"/>
               <head>Victo ſeculo. Chriſt his victorie ouer the world.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="301" facs="tcp:20154:174"/>A garland of thornes made faſt to a reed or bal bruſh, reſembleth a type of the paſſion of our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, ſignifieng his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie and euerlaſting kingdome, and his vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie ouer the world and ſathan the prince of this world, whom he vanquished.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="302" facs="tcp:20154:175"/>
               <head>Terriculum noxae. The feare of hurt.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="303" facs="tcp:20154:175"/>Pompeius Magnus being made head go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor of the armie,<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> &amp; ſent of Scilla into Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, behaued himſelfe not onely vigilantly, ſtoutly and valiantly, but alſo ſhewed himſelf a iuſt captaine with maruellous great equity. So that if he knew of any that went out of the campe on forraging, and either robbed, or committed any outragious fact, he would ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely puniſh them. Moreouer that he might reſtraine and bridle his ſcouts and poſts from oppreſſing of thoſe that they met withall, he marked or ſealed their ſwords with his owne ſignet which he wore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Hic terminus haerit. Here is the end of all things.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Leſt the increaſe and abounding of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, of honors, goods, and finally of all other things, ſhould by any meanes hinder noble men, &amp; wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they ſhould not ſomtimes think that they are mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all as well as others, all of them for the moſt part, haue inuented
<pb n="304" facs="tcp:20154:176"/>ſome certaine meanes or other, which may now and then put them in minde of death and of their ende. The which thing maiſter Boizius the kings chiefe taſter vſeth at this daie, hauing for his armes the forme of a blocke or peece of timber, caſt downe to the ground, with theſe wordes written about it, Here is the furtheſt bound or limit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="305" facs="tcp:20154:176"/>
               <head>Mihi pondera luxus. Exceſſe is burdenous to me.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Like as corne (as Seneca ſaith) is diuerſe times ouerwhelmed of it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> and the eares
<pb n="306" facs="tcp:20154:177"/>caſt downe thorow ouermuch rancknes, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the immoderate heaping vp of commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and pleaſures is hurtful to good wits, and to thoſe which in other reſpects carrie verie good mindes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Nil amplius optat. The contented man wiſheth for no more.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>This tipe or figure of nets or hayes wouen togither, may be referred to the metaphor going before: and doeth teach vs, that hee that liueth content with his own goods, doth eaſily deſpiſe and contemne the inordinate deſire of fraile and tranſitorie things.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="307" facs="tcp:20154:177"/>
               <head>Num flatus telluris honor. Is not honor a blaſt of winde?</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>There was an ancient cuſtome amongſt the Romaines, that to euerie gouernor of any countrey or prouince newly created, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulation ſake onely as a ſigne of good luck to enſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, ſhould be giuen, in honour of them ſeuen ſhillings to euerie one, a clot or turfe, a key and a ball or globe. The clot they gaue in token that the Magiſtrates ought to beſtow al their dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that meats ſhould not become dearer, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould remaine in the ſame
<pb n="308" facs="tcp:20154:178"/>price that they were, at that no dearth, want, nor hunger might ariſe. Moreouer, that the publike affaires might be moderate, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted with ſuch wiſedome and clemencie, as in giuing of a clot o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> peece of earth, they than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the deputie or gouernor for their fieldes, and corne. The key they gaue in token that he ought to expend and way of their liberty, and his owne authoritie in bidding and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. The ſphere or globe, they gaue to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his puiſſant right and authoritie. So Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander interpreted a globe or ſphere giuen him of Darius. Except wee had rather that the ſphere ſhould ſignifie the gouernment of ciuill pollicie, and martiall diſcipline.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="309" facs="tcp:20154:178"/>
               <head>Me pompae prouexit apex. The deſire of renowne hath promoted me, or ſet me forward.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>The Romaines ſuppoſed it the chiefeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of famous deedes, if they adorned their Emperors, captaines, knights, &amp; other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men ſoldiers, euery one notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding according to their dignity, degree &amp; place, with crownes
<pb n="310" facs="tcp:20154:179"/>or garlands, which they called <hi>militares co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronas,</hi> martiall crownes, or crownes of chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualrie. And becauſe they were ſignes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of their vertue, noble exploits, and inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible mindes: the chiefeſt and famouſt had their purtraitures, with their Apothegmes &amp; poſies, and that as well for the perpetuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of their worſhip, and ancienty as alſo for the oblectation, pleaſure, &amp; eſperance to thoſe that ſhould come after, attending &amp; ſeeking after the honor of vertue, with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward &amp; praiſe therof. Which things are eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially due to thoſe who are the reuengers, the patrons &amp; redeemers of the common wealth (which ought greatly to be regarded of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) The firſt crowne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was giuen, was called tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphall, which being platted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> laurel bowes, and berries, was offered to inuincible trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers. To whom it was lawfull, &amp; that by the decree of the ſenate, to ſolemne their triumph vp and downe the cittie in great charets, and wagons, as vanquiſhers, and ſubduers of their enimies: the ſenate being aduertiſed firſt of 5000. of their enimies to be ſlaine togitherin one battel. Which triumphant crowne, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of time, the Empire decreaſing, was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards interlaced with vnions, and diuerſe other precious ſtones. And laſt of all, it was
<pb n="311" facs="tcp:20154:179"/>changed from the natural laurell, into a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen laurell compaſſed about with a circle of gold, as is to be ſeene yet to this day in old coynes and pictures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <head>Merces ſublimis honorum. The reward of honor is great.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe that were deliuered, and had eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in any battell, gaue to the tribune, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor of the armie, who had valiantly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued
<pb n="312" facs="tcp:20154:180"/>their enimies, a triumphant crowne of graſſe. And albeit this garland, or crowne was of graſſe onely, it is to be thought notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that it waws compact of all manner of herbes and flowers that could be found in that place, after the armies were diſperſed, yet neuertheleſſe (as Plinie witneſſeth) it was the honorableſt of all the reſt, and hold in greateſt eſtimation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="313" facs="tcp:20154:180"/>
               <head>Seruati gratia Ciuis. The reward of him that had deliuered a cittie out of danger,</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>If any citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had deliuered his citty out of any ſingular da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger in battel, &amp; had preſerued it in ſafety, he was rewarded by another w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a crown or garland, platted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Oke leaues, becauſe in old time men liued of ſuch meats as the Okes yeelded.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="314" facs="tcp:20154:181"/>
               <head>Excidij turribus honos. The honor done to him had ſcaled the walles of his enimies.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>A crowne of gold repreſenting the forme of a wall with pinacles and turrets vpon it, was giuen by the Emperor or gouernour, or gouernor of the armie to him that by force, and armes, ſhould firſt cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbe vp vpon the wals of his enimies, or any way enter into their cittie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="315" facs="tcp:20154:181"/>
               <head>Hoc valli inſigne recepti. This was the reward of him that tooke the valley of his enimie.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>A crowne of gold alſo made in forme of a valey was giuen of the Emperor, or preſident of the hoſt, to him that could take the valley from his enimies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="316" facs="tcp:20154:182"/>
               <head>Claſſis monumenta ſubactae. The reward of him that boorded his enimies ſhippe.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſea fight whoſoeuer could firſt giue charge vpon his enimies nauie, or fleete, and enter his ſhippe armed, was crowned with a crowne of gold made like to the forepart of a ſhippe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="317" facs="tcp:20154:182"/>
               <head>In hunc intuens. Looke vpon this image.</head>
               <figure/>
               <p>The Egyptians were accuſtomed in their banquets and feaſtes to haue carried about with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an image or picture of death, &amp; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to euerie one, repeating theſe verſes.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="318" facs="tcp:20154:183"/>
                  <l>Marke and behold what thing you ſee,</l>
                  <l>a grimly ghoſt and fell,</l>
                  <l>Like vnto which you once ſhall be,</l>
                  <l>in darkeſome caue of hell.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Iſidorus reporteth alſo that at Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople there was a cuſtome,<note place="margin">Iſidorus.</note> to put the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in mind of his departure hence: The firſt day that he was to be crowned a certaine Maſon ſhould bring vnto him three or foure forts of ſtones, ſaying vnto him theſe words:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Oh noble Caeſar puiſſant king,</l>
                  <l>chooſe thou here preſently,</l>
                  <l>Of which ſtone ſhall thy graue be made,</l>
                  <l>wherein thou once ſhalt lie.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="319" facs="tcp:20154:183"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictoria limes. Victorie is the end.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>Epictetus the Philoſopher being aſked vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a time of Adrianus the Emperor wherfore the deade were crowned with garlands, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that they might declare, how that by death they had ouercome the labors, ſorrows and imminent heape of the cares of this life. Plinie alſo ſpeaketh of the ſame crowning of the dead, witneſſing that they were accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be offred vp after the ſame manner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="device">
               <pb n="320" facs="tcp:20154:184"/>
               <head>Spes alter a vitae. Hope of another life.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="321" facs="tcp:20154:184"/>Corne, graine, and ſeeds of ſundrie ſorts, being dead and caſt into the ground do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue, and ſpring againe: So mans bodie fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into the ground ſhall riſe againe in glory, in the laſt and general day of the reſurrection of the fleſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="322" facs="tcp:20154:185"/>
               <head>THE PVRTRATVRES OR Emblemes of Gabriel Simeon a Florentine.</head>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>Huc curſus fuit. This was the marke he ſhot at.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <q>HVC CVRSVS FVIT</q>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>As a man is greatly to loue and eſteeme him of whom he is deliuered from the danger of ſhipwracke, and brought into the quiet and ſafe hauen: ſo (as I coniecture) the inuentor
<pb n="323" facs="tcp:20154:185"/>of this ſimbole would ſignifie hereby, how for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate and happie he thought himſelfe, for that he was receiued into the ſeruice of the moſt famous Prince Emanuel Philibertus, duke of Sauoy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>Quis dicere laudes? Who can expreſſe his praiſes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>EL</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>This picture or ſigne of the croſſe (an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of Gods loue and fauour towards vs) being the proper enſigne of the duke of Sauoy, with this ſillable E L, in Hebrue ſignifying, God included in a ring of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garits, and ſundrie precious ſtones fetched
<pb n="324" facs="tcp:20154:186"/>from the Eaſt, and the Princes crowne vpon the top therof, doth aptly ſignifie the prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſedome and names of Emanuell duke of Sauoy, and the dutcheſſe Margaret, which Princes for their diuine gifts, no man can ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently praiſe or commend.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>Festina lentè. Make haſt but flowly.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Auguſtus Caeſar (a man farre from that headlong precipitancie, &amp; credulitie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by many Princes and Magiſtrates giuing cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite at the firſt aſſalt to the falſe ſuggeſtions of thei paraſites and flatterers, haue manie
<pb n="325" facs="tcp:20154:186"/>times done that which hath bene moſt impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and wicked) proteſting to obſerue a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and iuſt moderation in the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his common wealth, amongſt other monuments commanded a butterflie clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to a ſea crabbe to be ingrauen in gold, inſinuating by the ſlowneſſe of the one, a kind of temperancie and cold deliberation: and by the faſt flying of the other a certaine raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or headlong fury. By both which ioyned togither he ſignified, that a certaine meane or temperature in all things is verie needfull for a prince.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="326" facs="tcp:20154:187"/>
                  <head>Festina lentè. Make flowe haſt.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Inſteed of the ſea crab, and the butterflie of Auguſtus, Veſpaſian the emperour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a Dolphin and an Ankor in ſuch ſort (as here thou ſeeſt expreſſed) to be purtraied.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="327" facs="tcp:20154:187"/>
                  <head>Pacatum ipſa regam auitis vertutibus orbem. I will rule the world thorow the vertue of my anceſtors.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>By this ripe or figure of a Dolphin bearing the ſphere or globe of the world vpon his backe, in the forme of a ring or circle, marked with a diamant (being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peculiar armes of the houſe of Medicis) with the purtrature of the moone increaſing (being the enſigne of king Henrie) wherout two bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches do bud, one of a palme, in token of victory gotten, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other of an Oliue
<pb n="328" facs="tcp:20154:188"/>in hope of peace, with this egloge or pofie, <hi>Pacatum ipſe regam auitis virtutibus orbem,</hi> That is, I will gouerne the whole world in peace thorow the vertue and valour of my progenitors, is ſignified the famous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genie of king Dolphin, as well on his fathers fide, as alſo on his mothers, both their armes being reduced into one. Inſinuating by the moone increaſing the ſoueraigntie and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of the kings blood, by the diamant his inuincible vertue. Finally, by the ſphere or globe of the world his inexpugnable power and might. After which manner the ancient Romaines in times paſt did ſignifie the ſame thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="329" facs="tcp:20154:188"/>
                  <head>Fato prudentia maior. Wiſedome is of greater force then deſtonie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>I haue conſecrated the ſtarre incloſed with an adder or ſnake crowned, &amp; biting her taile, with this inſcription, <hi>Fato prudentia maior</hi> Wiſdome is of greater force then deſtenie it ſelfe, to the queene of France in token of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, &amp; that to ſignifie, that albeit fortune hath aduanced her highneſſe greatly, as being the daughter of ſuch noble parents, to wit, duke
<pb n="330" facs="tcp:20154:189"/>Vrbin, and dutcheſſe of Bologne, the nephew of ſuch a noble biſhoppe as was Clement the ſeuenth, and wife of the high and mightie Prince Henrie the ſecond king of France. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, the mother of ſuch and ſo many noble children, yet notwithſtanding, by her admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable vertue, modeſtie, &amp; clemencie, ſhe hath brought to paſſe that ſhe may worthely cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the greateſt praiſe of all the queenes of France that euer were.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="331" facs="tcp:20154:189"/>
                  <head>Mirandum natura opus. Nature is wonderfull in her worker.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>No purtrature (in my opinion) can better be aſcribed to the two Margarets, the one queene of Nauarre, the other of France, than the picture of a lillie crowned with two Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigolds ſprouting out of the ſides thereof, with theſe words, <hi>Mirandum naturae opus.</hi> Nature is wonderfull in her workes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="332" facs="tcp:20154:190"/>
                  <head>Simul &amp; ſemper. Togither and for euer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the tipe of the diamant is vnderſtood the loue and inuincible power of the king and queene of Nauarre: by the ſunne and moone, the excellencie of their actes, with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie &amp; permanence of their mutuall faith, and in diſſoluble amitie, with this inſcription, <hi>Simul &amp; ſemper,</hi> that is, liue peaceably to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither here, and liue for euer there.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="333" facs="tcp:20154:190"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>ΑΠΑΑΘΣ.</p>
                        <p>Without deccipt or guile.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>The armed hand hearing a ſword<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with this greek word ΑΠΑΑΝΟΣ without deceipt or guile, doth ſignifie he high Conſtable to haue bene moſt truſtie and faithfull to the king both in peace and in warres, and haue alwayes diſpoſed and ordered the affaires of France verie happely and proſperouſly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="334" facs="tcp:20154:191"/>
                  <head>Perimit &amp; tuetur. He flayeth and defendeth.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Setting before my eyes the wiſedome and magnanimitie of the duke of Guiſe, I haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented for his enſigne a round ſhield marked with a crowne, &amp; thruſt thorow with a ſword, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe words written round about the ſame, <hi>Peremit &amp; tuetur.</hi> He puniſheth the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſaueth the godly, that it may be knowne how valiant he is as wel in defending &amp; expugning of cities, as alſo in ouerthrowing and vanquiſhing of his enimies in warres and fought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n fields.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="335" facs="tcp:20154:191"/>
                  <head>Conſequitur quodcumque petit. She obtaineth whatſoeuer ſhe deſireth.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <q>CONSEQVITVR QVODCVNQV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> PETIT</q>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>Diana of Pictauia dutcheſſe of the Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinenſis aſcribed a dart to her ſelfe (which was the dart of Diana the goddeſſe) with this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, <hi>Conſequitur quodcunque petit.</hi> That is, ſhe obtaineth whatſoeuer ſhe wiſheth for or deſireth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="336" facs="tcp:20154:192"/>
                  <head>Ex vtroque Caefar. By both theſe Caeſar.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>By this Apothegme Caeſar is vnderſtoode, namely, how that by theſe two things, to wit, Weapons and good letters, hauing alwayes a watchfull eye to the execution of iuſtice, he became ruler ouer all the world.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="337" facs="tcp:20154:192"/>
                  <head>Solatur conſcientia &amp; finis. The conſcience and the end doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort a man.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Melphenſis a king cauſed a Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to bee pourtraied and ſet vp on high, with this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or poſie, <hi>Solatur conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia &amp; finis,</hi> that is, a good conſcience doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort a man in hope of the end. To ſignifie, that although he were depriued of all his riches, and expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="338" facs="tcp:20154:193"/>out of his kingdome, was notwithſtanding content with his fortune, and liued with a good conſcience, knowing that hee had well &amp; godly executed his office. and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence forth placing all his hope and truſt in the mercie of God, after his departure out of this life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>Scribit in marmore laeſus. The wounded man writeth in marble.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some are ſo puft vp and ſwelled with pride, truſting to their authoritie and riches, that they eſteeme the poore nothing at all, moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,
<pb n="339" facs="tcp:20154:193"/>deriding, &amp; iniuring euery one of meane eſtate, perſwading themſelues that either by reaſon of the pouertie of their parents and friends, or their owne indigencie and want, they ſhal neuer be able to reuenge the ſame, but muſt quickly forget it. But theſe tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts (for that is their proper name) are notablie decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in this their madnes: for time and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhall once teach them, that <hi>ſerò ſapiunt phriges,</hi> that they with the Phrigians are ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie too late, or els they ſhal learne by this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent picture of a man writing theſe wordes in marble ſtones, <hi>ſcribit in marmore laeſus.</hi> that is, being hurt, he recordeth the ſame in marble.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="340" facs="tcp:20154:194"/>
                  <head>Coſi viuo piacer conduce à morte. So doth pleaſant delights leade to deſtruction.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Vnder the figure of the butterflie, who ſo much delighteth in the brightnes of the fire, that of her owne accord ſhe caſteth her ſelfe into the ſame, and ſo is burned: may be ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, how that a man who goeth about, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth
<pb n="341" facs="tcp:20154:194"/>euerie thing without deliberation and choice, getteth many times to himſelf ſhame, reproch and deſtruction withall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>Amico ficto nulla fit iniuria. No wrong to a fained friend.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>To him that by all meanes and pollicies doth faine and diſſemble friendſhip, agreeth moſt notablie the figure of a masker or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed, man (which ſignifieth the deceit of
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:20154:195"/>the mind) whom another doth ſo wound with a ſtaffe, that he caſteth downe his counterfet viſage, together with theſe wordes, <hi>Amico ficto nulla fit iniuria.</hi> It is no wrong done to a counterfet friend.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>Ignis gladio non fodiendus. The fire is not to be ſtirred with a ſword.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>This preſent picture of a man ſtirring the fire with the point of his ſword, ſo as the ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles thereof ariſing, burne out one of his eies,
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:20154:195"/>doth ſignifie and point out vnto vs the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rellous and contentious fellowes, with this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothegme out of the life of Pythagoras, <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis gladio non eſt fodiendus.</hi> The fire is not to be ſtirred with a ſword.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>Statêre aerdo non tranſiliendus. The ballance is not to be ouerladen with waight.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe that be wicked &amp; of euil conſcience, it is moſt certaine, doe neither keepe nor obſerue anie meane, and therefore for the
<pb n="344" facs="tcp:20154:196"/>moſt, they proue their end to be miſerable, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as a paire of ballance or waights (which the Latines and the Tuſcans call a Statera) if you lade the one more then is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient with waight, it ſtraight waie breaketh in peeces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>Sic vos non vobis. You haue the paines, but others haue the profite.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>If anie man will aſcribe the memorable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits of another man to the rulers or gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, the ſame may verie aptly bee expreſſed by a yoke of oxen drawing the plowe. With this verſe out of Virgil, <hi>Sic vos non vobis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="345" facs="tcp:20154:196"/>
                  <head>Solus promeritus. One deſerueth the praiſe alone.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Vpon the other ſide, if I ſhould inuent a ſit ſymbole, to a gentle, noble, bolde, and wiſe Captaine, who moued thereto of his owne valour, hath ſuſtained and borne the whole burthen of the battell with his owne handes (which thing many of our age haue done) I would pourtraie three or foure horſes running, of whome one alone ſhoulde runne before all the reſt, and firſt come to the place
<pb n="346" facs="tcp:20154:197"/>appointed, with theſe wordes, <hi>Solus prome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus,</hi> that is, he alone hath deſerued the beſt Imitating herein the cuſtome of the ancient Romanes, who exerciſed themſelues to run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in liſts, and alſo the Flotentines, who vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the great and ſolemne feaſt daie of Saint Iohn Baptiſt, doe exerciſe the like riding and courſing of horſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="347" facs="tcp:20154:197"/>
                  <head>Aut Caeſar aut nihil. Either Caſar or nothing.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Cęſar Borgia Duke of Valentia, going about to make it knowen that hee had decreed to bring deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the world, or els to do ſom what worthy of remembrance, enuying Iulius Cęſar for vndertaking ſuch high things, vſed this Apothegme, <hi>Aut Caeſar aut nihil,</hi> and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any other ſymbole, wherto we thought
<pb n="448" facs="tcp:20154:198"/>good to adde this, as if an armed ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld be painted, holding in the one hand the world, figuring as it were the monarchy of Iulius Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, in the other hand a paper filled with ooo, which by it ſelfe ſignifieth nothing, but anex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with another figure of Arithmetike, it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth ſome thing. And ſurelie it was verie ſignificant. For the bolde and vnwiſe man at the length broght himſelf to nothing indeed, as hee was accuſtomed to ſaie in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegme, for almoſt in the midſt of his youth he was ſlaine in the kingdome of Nauarre. V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon whoſe tombe was written this Epitaph:</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Borgia Caeſar ſometime I was,</l>
                     <l>A Cęſar right in deede and name,</l>
                     <l>Either Caeſar or nothing ile bring to pas,</l>
                     <l>both which he was, then died w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhame.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="349" facs="tcp:20154:198"/>
                  <head>Sola facta ſolum Deum ſequor. Being a lone woman, I will followe God alone.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Bone a moſt famous and noble woman of Sauoy, and moother to Iohn Galeaz Duke of Milan, after her husbandes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſſe, cauſed a coine to bee made (which the people there doe call a teſtone) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the one ſide whereof was a phenixe pourtraied with theſe wordes: <hi>Sola fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta ſolum Deum ſequor.</hi> Signifieng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>erby,
<pb n="350" facs="tcp:20154:199"/>that as the Phenix is alone her ſelfe in the world, ſo ſhe being made a widow by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of her husband, voweth her ſelfe to liue for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with God alone.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>Pas à pas. Foote by foote.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>natus king of Scicilie deſirous to haue it knowen that he conceiued hope to become a mightier prince thou yet hee was, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape and ouercome all dangers and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="351" facs="tcp:20154:199"/>commanded his Enſigne or ſymbole to be pourtraied in forme of an ox, carrying his cogniſance vpon his necke, with theſe words annexed, <hi>Pas à pas,</hi> Foote by foote, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby, that the oxe, albeit verie ſlowlie, doth vndertake notwithſtanding manie a great and tedious iourney.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>Ditat ſeruata fides. Fidelitie inricheth.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>A certaine man going about to ſhewe what loialtie, obedience, and faithfull ſeruice, hee had performed towardes his maiſter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee was greatlie inriched, for his
<pb n="352" facs="tcp:20154:200"/>Enſigne, pourtraied two handes embracing a certain hearb called Semper viueus (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by was ſignified plentie of all thinges) with theſe wordes, <hi>Ditat ſeruata fides,</hi> that is, Loialtie and truth purchaſeth great riches.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ireſcit vulnere virtus. Veritie increaſeth when it is oppreſſed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>A certain other man of a mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne eſtate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſecuted of enuie, through the common ignorance of men for his vertue and good deedes (as almoſt all the godlie are) and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſignifie, that how much the more hee
<pb n="353" facs="tcp:20154:200"/>was perſecuted, ſo much the more he woulde publiſh and ſhew forth his vertue and godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, pictured a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n treading vnder his feete the plant of an hear be, which the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries call Aceroſa, the Latines Rumice, the Greekes Oxalida, the Florentins Agreſtina, with this ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, <hi>Vireſcit vulnere virtus,</hi> that is, vertue how much the more it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, ſo much the more it flouriſheth and increaſeth: following heerein the nature of th t hear be, which how much the more it is troden vpon, ſo much the more greene it is. Which ſimbole ſometime the Lord Legat of Prat high Chancellor of France vſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="354" facs="tcp:20154:201"/>
                  <head>Eſto tienne ſu remedio, y non yo. The Hart hath his remedie, but ſcue hath none.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Hart ſtroke thorough with an arrow, &amp; eating of a branch or leafe of Dictanus (which is an hearbe growing abundantly in Candia, or the Iland of Creta, which being eaten of a hart, his wounds are immediatly healed) with this inſcription, <hi>Eſto tienne ſu remedio, y non yo,</hi> that is, the heart here hath helpe, but my wounde is incurable, may bee a figure or
<pb n="355" facs="tcp:20154:201"/>ſimbole of loue that can neuer be healed: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding to that verſe of Ouid in his Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſis, wherein Phoebus bewraieth his loue towards Daphnes:</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Wo to me that haggard loue,</l>
                     <l>which ſets our mindes on fire,</l>
                     <l>Cannot be healed by hearbes or rootes,</l>
                     <l>nor druggie potions dire.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="356" facs="tcp:20154:202"/>
                  <head>Ingenium ſuperat vires. Wit or pollicie excelleth ſtrength.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fernandus Conſaluus in the laſt Neopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan warres, ſhewed himſelfe not onely a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and valiant Captaine, but alſo verie wiſe and p l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ike: inſomuch that hee at chieued verieth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>plie many great battels, who was ſo
<pb n="357" facs="tcp:20154:202"/>farre from fearing leaſt his pollicie which hee vſed ſhuld be eſpied, that he gaue for his ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole a bow which was wont to bee bent with ſtrings or cordes, this apothogme beeing ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereto, <hi>Ingenium ſuperat vires,</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie is of greater force then ſtrength.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>Qui me alit, me extinguit. He that nouriſheth me, killeth me.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the exile or banniſhment of the Helueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="458" facs="tcp:20154:203"/>neere Millan, after the deceaſſe of Francis their king, the Lord of Saint Valier, the father of the Ladie Diana of Poitiers, Dutcheſſe of Valentinois, and gouernour ouer an hundreth noble knightes, carried a ſtandard about, wherein was pictured a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Torch turned vpſide downe, the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xe mel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing and quenching the ſame, with this ſentence. <hi>Qui me alit, me extinguit,</hi> that is, he that feedeth me, killeth me. Which ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole was framed for a certain noble womans ſake, willing to inſinuate hereby, that as her beautie and comelines did pleaſe his minde, ſo might it caſt him into danger of his life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>Furor fit laeſa ſepiùs patientia. Patience being moued is turned into anger.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some men are ſo fooliſh and raſh bolde or
<pb n="359" facs="tcp:20154:203"/>haſtie, as well in wordes as in deedes, that they will not ſticke to anoie the quieteſt, the modeſt, and the godlieſt men that be: which thing falleth out now and then to their owne hurt, is it did once to a young man, who too vehemently purſuing a Ram, was hurt of him for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> labour, prouing in deede that this olde Adage is true, <hi>Furor fit laeſa ſaepiùs pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientia,</hi> Patience being moued is turned into furie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="360" facs="tcp:20154:204"/>
                  <head>Frons hominem praefert. The face ſheweth a mans diſpoſition.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe that haue writ of the ſecretes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and of the ſignes of phiſognomie (as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle beareth witnes) ſaie, that the forhead doth ſhew euerie mans diſpoſition or inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therefore a narowe ſlender forehad is a ſigne of a fooliſh man, vncleane, and like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſwine, giuen altogether to the bellie. A forehead too large like an oxe, is a ſigne of a groſſe and dull wit and vnderſtanding. A
<pb n="361" facs="tcp:20154:204"/>forehead long ſheweth a man to be very gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and docile, hanging downe ouer the eies, effeminate and womanniſhnes. Being round, it ſignifieth a wicked man and vnconſtant. Plaine and bare, a man ambicious, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of vaine glorie. Bald to the middeſt, a man furious and angrie. Wrinckled or riue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, a heauie and ſleepie man. Soft, a man merrie, gentle and pleaſant. Being rough, and in ſome places full of little freckles, or ſpots, a craftie man, couetous, and a malicious foole. Poliſhed and as it were hued, and euen, a man ſecure or careleſſe. Being foure ſquare in a reaſonable quantitie, a valiant man, wiſe, and honeſt: which indices or tokens of the forehead moued me to inuent this ſimbole, with this poſie: <hi>Frons hominem praefert,</hi> A mans face ſheweth what he is.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="362" facs="tcp:20154:205"/>
                  <head>Bis dat qui tempestiuè donat. He giueth twiſe that giueth in time.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are ſome men ſo haſtie, ſo vnadui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſo vnſeaſonable in doing of good turnes vnto others, that how little a man nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth their help, ſo much the more readie are they to gratifie him with gifts, and take great pleaſure in performing the leſt point of their duetie towards him: and that (as I ſuppoſe) either for that they ſtand in hope, afterwards of reaping ſome commoditie by them, or elſe
<pb n="363" facs="tcp:20154:205"/>at the leaſt to be repaid againe with the moſt. But if they chance to eſpie the ſame man f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into miſerie, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe curſſed men will turne away their faces from h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m: and if the poore man aſke them their helpe, either they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll caſt in his teeth their former be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>efites, or elſe mocke and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ide the poore wretch, either elſe they will inuent and faine ſome reaſon or other, ſo that the poore man dares neuer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter come in their ſight againe. Theſe men doubtleſſe are not parents, not true friends, nay not men, but rather brute beaſtes vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to liue, who it behoueth to looke vpon, and to remember this ſimbole of a noble man indeede, who ſeing a poore man fallen downe lifted him vp againe himſelfe, with this poſie, <hi>Bis dat, qui tempestiuè donat,</hi> that is, he giueth twiſe that giueth in time. Becauſe that ought to be counted a double and immortall merite, which in time of neceſſitie doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite another without any hope or expectation of reward.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="364" facs="tcp:20154:206"/>
                  <head>Improbus à nullo flectitur obſequio. The wicked is moued to mercie with no entretie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe that are ſo cruell. ſo hard harted, ſo auſtere and wicked, that although a man giue them all obedience, yet will not vouchſafe to ſhew him any compaſſion, are worthie truely to haue for their ſimbole the image of death, who ſlayeth all men, euen him that prayeth and beſeecheth with his hands lifted vp, and knees touching the ground, with theſe words,
<pb n="366" facs="tcp:20154:206"/>
                     <hi>Improbus à nullo ſlectitur obſequio.</hi> The wicked is not moued to compaſſion by any diligence, obedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce, or petition.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <head>Sic maiora cedunt. Thus the greater giueth place.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Goſhauke carried amongſt a companie of Falcons with this inſcription, <hi>Sic maiora cedunt,</hi> ſo great thinges giue place to the ſmall, doth ſignifie that true nobilitie doth
<pb n="366" facs="tcp:20154:207"/>not conſiſt in riches, or authoritie, but in the excellencie of the mind, for ſuch is the nature and propertie of the Goſhauke, that ſhe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth all birds farre greater then her ſelfe out of all dangers whereto they are ſubiect.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="367" facs="tcp:20154:207"/>
                  <head>Malè parta, malè dilabuntur. Things euill got, are as euill ſpent.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>A certaine Ape being brought vp in a vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters houſe, who was altogither delighted in counting of his money, ſpying vpon a time his maſter playing, and toying with his money vpon a table, when his maſter was at dinner he crept in at a window, and got him to the heape of money, where imitating his maſter,
<pb n="370" facs="tcp:20154:208"/>after that he had delighted himſelfe enough with turning and toſſing the money to and fro, at the laſt he began to throw it out at the window into the ſtreete as faſt as he could. With which ſight, whether the paſſingers by were more delighted, or the Vſurer grieued, I liſt not here to debate, hauing enough to do to laugh at this vſurer, &amp; the like, who heape vp great ſummes of money, &amp; leaue it either to their brother or nephewe, or elſe to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, whoremaſters, gluttons and the like, ſcarſely euer remembring this excellent and golden ſentence, <hi>Malè parta, malè dilu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buntur,</hi> Things euill got, are euill ſpent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="371" facs="tcp:20154:208"/>
                  <head>Expetendae opes vt dignis largiamur. Riches are to be deſired, that wee may giue to thoſe that deſerue.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>I haue heard that famous noble man, Lord Mathew Balbanus of Lucquois, reporte many times of himſelfe, that he praied God daily to grant him no exceſſe or abundance of riches,
<pb n="372" facs="tcp:20154:209"/>except it woulde pleaſe him to giue him alſo both will and reaſon to vſe them. A deſire and petition doubtleſſe, beſeeming not onely a priuate noble man, but alſo a prince himſelfe: whoſe gracious fauour is ſo much the more to bee eſteemed, how much the more hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rmeth the ſame in effect, in deede, and in worde: at home keeping and maintaining a great number of learned men, abroad ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting many with great ſtipends. Wherefore it ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>med good to vs to dedicate this Simbole to him, to wit, the figure of a hande in the aire, pouring out mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e out of a cup vppon a h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, and a booke lying vppon an altar, with theſe wordes, <hi>Expetendae opes vt dignis largiamur,</hi> Riches are to be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſired, that we may giue them to thoſe that are worthie. The altar repreſenting the worthines of men, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tters or in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mes (which thing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t and the booke doo inſinuate) and the cup flowing ouer, doeth euidently ſignifie the liberalitie of a no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le perſonage.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="273" facs="tcp:20154:209"/>
                  <head>Mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſceptra ligonibus aequans. Death maketh King Scep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers equall to poore mens mattock<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Princes, noble men, rich men, and finallie all men of what authoritie or condition ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue they be, ought diligently to looke into this picture of a Kings ſcepter, ioyned with a poore mans mattocke with a deaths heade betwixt them both, with theſe wordes: <hi>Mors ſceptra ligonibus aequans,</hi> Death maketh Kings ſcepters equall to pore mens mattocks.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="device">
                  <pb n="374" facs="tcp:20154:210"/>
                  <head>Ingratis ſeruire nefas. It is an euill thing to ſerue an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull perſon.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure/>
                  </p>
                  <p>This prouerbe is common euerie where<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Poiſon lurketh in the taile. Wherefore I will heere make an ende of theſe ſimboles with this laſt: wherein I may compare the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude of ſome to the viper, who killeth the male in copulation, and is her ſelfe kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of the fruit which ſhee conceiueth in her bellie. Wherefore as well ſhee and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men haue iuſt cauſe to burſt foorth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe or the like complaintes, <hi>Ingrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſeruire nefas,</hi> It is a hell to ſerue the ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20154:210"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
